<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rebellion strip't and whipt, through all its principles and pretences; from the first to the last. By way of appeale to the consciences of the City of London in particular, and the whole kingdom in generall. In the behalfe of his most sacred Majesty, and the Church now trampled on by traytors.</title>
            <author>Rexophilus Londinatus, Christianus protestans.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E476_28</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203367</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863338</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863338</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115533</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92298)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115533)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 76:E476[28])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rebellion strip't and whipt, through all its principles and pretences; from the first to the last. By way of appeale to the consciences of the City of London in particular, and the whole kingdom in generall. In the behalfe of his most sacred Majesty, and the Church now trampled on by traytors.</title>
                  <author>Rexophilus Londinatus, Christianus protestans.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeere. 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To all true-hearted Englishmen" signed: Rexophilus Londinatus Christianus protestans.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 16".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115533:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REBELLION STRIP'T AND WHIPT, THROUGH All its Principles and Pretences; From the firſt to the laſt.</p>
            <p>By way of Appeale to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the City of LONDON in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and the whole Kingdom in generall.</p>
            <p>In the behalfe of his moſt Sacred MAjESTY, and the Church now trampled on by Traytors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pro</hi> ARIS <hi>et</hi> FOCIS.</p>
            <p>Printed in the yeere. 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115533:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115533:2"/>
            <head>To all true-hearted Engliſhmen, of what degree or qualitie ſoever, eſpecially to each particular Citizen of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous and friendly Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FOr ſo my believing charitie perſwadeth me to ſtyle you, although my mean and inconſiderable deſerts cannot hope to lay claim to the title;</p>
            <p>As it is a certaine truth for our comfort, that man's paſſive extremitie, is Gods active opportunitie, deliverance then ſtepping in, when in our apprehenſions wee are paſt hopes of being delivered; ſo it is as neceſſary a truth to be practiſed, that when Kingdomes, Cities, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies or friends are moſt paſſive under the extremitie of accumulative miſeries, threatning ruine and deſolation; then to be moſt active in our aſſiſtance, counſell, and to our power, deliveranco. Such like thoughts as theſe poſſeſſing me in theſe unhappieſt of unhappy times, wherein a generally-feared deſtruction hangeth over our heads like a ſharp pointed ſword, only by a ſmall thread, perſwaded me with the poore widow (my abilities not being able to beſtow more) to caſt in this my following mite; and if it ſhall (though in it ſelfe worthleſſe) prove by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring operation of Gods Spirit upon the hearts of men, in the leaſt manner, inſtrumentally contributary to the reformation of ſome infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of others, and a deſired reſtoration of the whole Kingdome in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, the City of <hi>London</hi> in particular, where I received my firſt birth and being, to their ancient honour, and former truth and peace, return your thankes to the Lord of heaven and earth, the fountaine of all Mercies, and pray for the Eternall happineſſe of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your reall friend, Country-man, and fellow Citizen,</hi> Rexophilus Londinatus Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Proteſtans.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Maii prim. <hi>1648.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:115533:3"/>
            <q>
               <l>— Ne inutilis olim</l>
               <l>vixiſſe videar —</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>25 Proverbs 11.</hi>
               </bibl>A word ſpoken in ſeaſon is like apples of Gold in pictures of Silver.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>122 Pſalme 8.</hi>
               </bibl>For my brethren and companions ſakes will I now ſay, peace bee within thy walls.</q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115533:3"/>
            <p>WHen the Hebrew-tongued bells ſadly invite the Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſiſtance of others to a pacification of that rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Element, Fire,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Hebrew Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters muſt bee read back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
                  <p>A Cuſtome in England to ring bels back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward when houſes are on fire.</p>
               </note> deſtructively active beyond its legall bounds, and a reduction of it to its proper center and due obedience; who will not (unleſſe ſome whoſe preventing care is little about their own, and carefull pitty leſſe imployed about others ruines) willingly contribute their quenching paines? Nay, who (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept others as miſerably deſtitute of honeſty as wealth, whoſe ſtrangely malicious mindes repine at the fruitfull induſtry, ſmiling proſperity of others, and whoſe irregular expectations hope to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the defect of their own wealth, and boy up their almoſt irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verably ſunk eſtates, by a generally concurring deſtruction) will not ſubſcribe to a voluntary demolition of their proper and more peculiar buildings; only to anticipate the devaſtation of others by that mercileſſe raging tyrant?</p>
            <p>When the angry windes begin to vent their ſpleen, and the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive ſurges which not long before were united into one only unfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed face, like ſlaves forced to a degeneration, are compelled by thoſe powerfully Commanding Maſters, into high ſwelling frowns, and deep-furrowed wrinkles, thereby menacing ruine to all float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing travellers in that uncertain watery region; Will not then all obliged, and reſolved guides, <hi>Vela moderantes per aequoris undas,</hi> unleſſe ſome who with too much eaſe can change ingagements of publike preſervation, into permiſſive if not active reſolutions of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, or others whoſe winding limbs embarqued on gainfull pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate hopes, or aguiſh loſing fears can comply with every rouling wave, thereby in vain expecting in a Fly-boat of neutralitie to ſwim ſafely to a ſelf-ſecuring ſhore; will not all except ſuch, conſult a prevention of ſuch a univerſally-threaten'd deſtruction?</p>
            <p>My deareſt Country-men, England <hi>hoc momento temporis</hi> (O that Fame could give my Pen the lye! but alas, alas, experience already hath and ſtill doth afford us too too certain grounds evidencing its truth) is at this very day become a ſad paralell of theſe preceding lines; England not long ſince famous abroad, happy at home, even beyond <hi>(ſi foelicitatem noverit)</hi> deſire of additionall happineſſe, for its united domeſtick ſtructures; I mean its Monarchicall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment compacted into ſo ſweetly agreeing,<note n="*" place="margin">King, Lord and Common in Parliamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> diſproportion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d proportion, that ſetting aſide thoſe <hi>Concomitantes Regnorum deva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatores,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115533:4"/>
thoſe deſtroyers of men and Kingdomes, Ambition, Envy, and Sedition, which blind the judgements ſight, enforcing it to a partiall (if not an envious) conſtruction of the beſt things) the moſt prying eye could not diſcern the<note n="*" place="margin">Pooreſt men.</note> humbleſt ſtone remedileſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſs'd by an oppreſſing<note n="*" place="margin">Rich per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> Superiour, or higheſt advanced pina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle proudly ſcorning inferiour ſubjected materialls without a check from the maſter builder, I mean the eſtabliſhed law, whoſe enlive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>fonſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> origo,</hi> is our Soveraigne Lord, King <hi>Charles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sine quo nulla nova fuit eſt Angliâ lex<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> erit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> 9. chap. 1. v.</note>This England <hi>quis non talia ſcribendo lachrymarum flumina mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet?</hi> who can forbeare wiſhing with the Prophet, That his head were full of water, and his eyes a fountain of tears to weep for his Native Country? by the beginning Sparcks of an unfortunate Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern fire-brand (ſtrange it is, that ſo cold, and almoſt benumming a climate ſhould yield ſuch nimbly-devouring fire) intermixing in its conſuming progreſſe with unnaturally connaturalizing materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls, by degrees grown almoſt into one entire flame.</p>
            <p>This winged Veſſell truly ſtyled Europ's Soveraigne, whoſe ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſayles not long ſince were filled even to envy, and admiration of all round about her, by long continuing, uninterrupted ſuccesfull gales; At laſt by the enforcement of rigid neceſſitie, juſtly ſteering its powerfully commanding courſe for its command proceeded from a<note n="*" place="margin">Commiſſion from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie.</note> Juſt power, neere the<note n="*" place="margin">Scotland.</note> Calidonian waters, met with ſome ſurly oppoſing gufts, high-working ambitious and rebellious waves, which not wanting a concurring aſſiſtance, and incouragement from other mutinous ſpirits (ſtrange it is that children of the ſame wombe ſhould rend the very bowels of their naturall parent upon the unreaſonable invitation of aliens) accompanying the ſame Fleet with this Royall Pilot, denyed to ſtrike ſayle, or expreſſe obedience to his lawfull commands: Which ſtrange and unnaturall oppoſition increaſing like ſnow roul'd from place to place, even to a monſtrous heap (by the ſenſleſly aſſiſting and furiouſly active hands of ſuch perſons) was ſoon, howſoever diſſolved by the favourable breath, and gracious condeſcentions beyond expectation of the Royall Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mander; himſelf, as it ſeemed, having a breſt more affected with the loſſe of any under his command, however in their obedience re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant, although I cannot but confeſſe, that many of that Nation were, and by their loyall words and deeds then did expreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115533:4"/>
repugnant to ſuch a repugnancy, than with the loſſe of part of his Commanding power. Soon after which theſe two un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall oppoſites met in mutuall embraces, and a pacification; and becauſe their reciprocall agreement was confirmed by the agreeing ſuffrages of the ſupreameſt Court, I will here <hi>ſilentium tenere,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain my pen from being further inquiſitive, Whether or no it was an act lawfull, and that warranted alſo by religion, reaſon and law in them, not only to deny obedience unto, but oppoſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of their lawfull (for now my expreſſions ſhall be plain to the apprehenſions of every one) and Native Soveraigne; or Whether it were not an action abſolutely neceſſary in their Prince, both in reſpect of religions, reaſons, lawes, and his honours vindication to demand a reaſon thereof, and that not proving ſatisfactory, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch an oppoſition.</p>
            <p>However I ſhall be bold to adde thus much, that if amidſt the troubled waters of another Nation, England then labouring with the almoſt unavoydable effects of a long continuing peace (a ſupine ſecuritie) with its adjuncts; as erroneous practices, overſights, miſcarriages in ſome particular Miniſters of State, as what Nation can plead a totall freedom from ſome intervening corruptions and Juſtice-perverting inſtruments? If by the additional aggravations of theſe Errours and miſtakes by the Ambition &amp; faction of ſome, who the better to facilitate a progreſſe in their own deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gnes, loudly ſpake to the undiſtinguiſhing multitude, that ſuch deviations from particular lawes, were but intentions (but upon what rationall ground I know not) of ſubverting the whole frame of the Law. If ſuch like ſtormes in England proved furthering inſtruments to purchaſe them a Calme, and a Serene Kingdome; If they beyond a probability of former hopes in this very opportunitie of opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, obtained their owne deſires from the unparalell'd favour of their Soveraigne; It were to be wiſhed that they then had rather remained ſatisfied with the poſſeſſion of ſo much happineſſe, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to God, the fountain of all bleſſings, thankfulneſſe for ſo great a mercy, ſtudying expreſſive gratitude by obedientiall and loyall actions to their Prince, for ſuch gracious manifeſtations, than like phanatick people, who havving mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly quenched fire begun in their own houſes, and thereby prevented a mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ruine; Not ſatisfied therewith (as if the miſery of others could adde perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitie to their procured happineſſe;) caſt fire-balls ſo long into their Neighbours dwellings, untill in it its furiouſly-devouring race it returne where it firſt began; Which, if God for ingratitude, and other concomitant ſins, as he is juſt without
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115533:5"/>
reſpect of perſons, ſhould in the revolution of future time permit; what mercy (although his mercy is above his juſtice) can they with confidence hope from him, who with ſo much neglect, I had almoſt written, impudence, have ſlighted his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours? Or what pittying aſſiſtance can they expect others ſhould ſhew unto them, who never ſuppoſed themſelves contentedly happy in their own particular inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, untill they had endeavoured, nay effected the generall unhappineſs of others?</p>
            <q>
               <l>Deus neceſſitatis cauſam talis avertat oro;</l>
               <l>O Lord prevent the occaſion of ſuch a neceſſitous aſſiſtance.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Further, all things conſidered, rather than expoſe themſelves to future hazards, it might have been, and ſtill may be a conſideration worthy their thoughts, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>praevidere,</hi> Whether or no in after ages, when hot fiery diſputing paſſions ſhall be lull'd aſleep, when mens imbittered ſpirits ſhall by well poyzed impartiall judgements be ſtopp'd from irregular verball excurſions, when private intereſts ſhall freely and unanimouſly reſolve themſelves into the generally reall good of the publike, Whether or no then their Succeſſours reflecting upon ſuch paſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and their Circumſtantiall means alſo made uſe of, probably may not both in their private diſcourſes eſteeme, and in publike generall Counſells cenſure, their favours,<note place="margin">Examples to this effect, our Nation hath many, and it is believed theirs is not without ſome few pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents.</note> or if they wil reformation, or rather alteration in government (Now free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theirs by the voluntary and graciouſly Confirming grant of his Majeſty) to bee but the enforced iſſue of griping neceſſitie, and the purchaſe of a menacing bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhed Sword, and becauſe ſo enforced, reſolve them as Null; and therefore for the Prevention hereof, that in the judicious ballances of after times they may not (to their laſting diſhonour) be found too light. It had been, and as yet may be a well becomming policie in them to be fruitfull in ſucceeding actions of loyall thankfulneſſe; <hi>Eſtote prudentes praeſtat, eſſe Promethium quam Epimethium;</hi> Too late penitentiall experience is but a ſadning miſtris.</p>
            <p>Therefore to this purpoſe before the houre-glaſſe of ſuch an opportunity is irrecoverably paſt, and its ſands quite ſpent; It were a ſeaſonable wiſh that they would take into their ſerious conſiderations, even their own loving Compellation and title of <hi>Brethren,</hi> and indeed wee are no leſſe, having one politicall Father the King, who is <hi>amborum pater regnorum,</hi> to whom we owe obedience by the law of God, and the lands, which being undoubtedly true;</p>
            <p>That they would make good that title by affectionate fraternall actions expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves brethren, <hi>Affectione reali activa<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non titulari ſolummodo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That their deeds ſpeaking the language of enemies, like <hi>Cain</hi>'s dealing with <hi>Abel,</hi> may no longer contradict their tongues expreſſion, Ceremoniouſly, if not treacherouſly tearming us brethren, that they <hi>Sub ſpecie fraterni nominis,</hi> as hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wee have had grounds to ſuſpect, may with more facilitie deceive the credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and the rather now becauſe it is murmured abroad, that <hi>Englands</hi> preſent miſeries, by their fighting and Covenanting aſſiſtance have received much addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; It concerneth them, <hi>non verba ſolummodo, ſed facta dicere,</hi> for <hi>non proſunt verba quum contraeria facta videmus;</hi> Therefore it were to bee deſired, that they would obey the command of Chriſt, to differ no longer, nor fall into new fractions, or further factions, becauſe we are brethren. And to this purpoſe it is expected as well for their own vindication (I mean not the whole Nation, for many thouſands therein
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115533:5"/>
have made good their conſtant loyalty to their King really, not ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bally, but all ſuch in that Nation whoſe conſciences cannot but whiſper themſelves neceſſarily concerned in ſuch a vindication, as requeſted, for their Brethrens aſſiſtance, that they would really and poſitively not with intermixed, uncertain diſtinctions, doubtfull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, ambiguous tearms, which like wax from the Seal, may be apted to any conſtruction, thereby owning the Jeſuit (whom they ſeem ſo much to deteſt) for their Parent; but on the contrary, that <hi>plene plane<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſine equivocatione,</hi> without mental reſervation or premiſed evaſion declare: and becauſe <hi>mera declaratio ſine actu inutilis &amp; otioſa,</hi> words in ſuch a caſe are ayery nothings, accordingly to act, for the reſtoration of our Proteſtant Religion to its generally practicall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, unity and uniformity; his royall Majeſty, their and our dread Soveraign, now (<hi>horreſco ſcribere!</hi> a reſtrained Priſoner) to his royall Prerogative and Rights by the Law of the Land, juſtly and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly manifeſted to be his: his Subjects, <hi>ſingulatim,</hi> and their fellow Subjects, to their ancient Liberties, Proprieties and Immunities, by the ſame Law really theirs; and in the conjunction of ſuch loyall affections, and really performed actions, the three Kingdoms to an entire Peace and undeniable Truth, according to the trueſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their own ſolemn League and Covenant, which being by their contributed aſſiſtance forwarded to a perfect conſummation, we ſhall return thanks to God for his exceeding bountifull expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſuch a mercy and gratification to them, as Inſtruments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing thereunto; hoping that we ſhall not need to put them in mind, that our hopes onely are, that ſuch kind of auxiliary affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will proceed meerly out of loyall affections to his Majeſty, and love to us their Brethren, and not from an intent commandingly to incorporate themſelves into <hi>Englands</hi> Priviledges, Freedoms, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Wealth; therefore at preſent ſhall have no occaſion to acquaint them, that <hi>Englands</hi> birth-right will not be ſold upon une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall terms, to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>O thou God of all Spirits, grant to them and us thy aſſiſting grace, that we may obey thee O Lord, who art the King of heaven and earth, in all things, for thy own ſake, according to thine own rule, and King <hi>Charles</hi> our Soveraign, thy ſubſtitute upon earth, for thy ſake, that ſo all of us guided by one Law of truth, thy will reveil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in thy Word, governed by him our King according to the truth of Law eſtabliſhed, and all our multiplied ſinnes againſt thee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115533:6"/>
being pardoned, treaſon and rebellion againſt his Majeſty buried in an unrepealable Act of oblivion, we may for the future live in piety and godlineſſe towards thee our God, in obedience and loyalty to his Majeſty, in unity, peace and concord (like Brethren) one among another, <hi>Amem, Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I return to <hi>England,</hi> which ſtill remaineth paſſive under a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannically waſting fire, and like a Ship ſtill toſſed to and fro by ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging tempeſtuous windes; it's true Religion by Law eſtabliſhed, it's really fundamentall Lawes, reſpecting both Prince and People, his juſt Rights, and the Subjects moſt certain and generally contenting Liberties approaching neer to a diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though not a deſtruction, (for <hi>magna veritas &amp; prevalebit,</hi> the gates of hell ſhall never be able to prevail againſt truth) being ready to ſink into an <hi>Aristocraticall</hi> bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, or <hi>Anarchicall</hi> bottomles Sea: Therefore (my dear Country-men) that I might not appear like an uncharitable Travellour, paſſing tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a Town contracted by fire into one flame, without obſervation, pitty, or according to my preſent poor ability, ſome aſſiſtance; or that I may not ſeem careleſſe to ſail by a diſtreſſed Veſſell, loſt almoſt in the deep, by the violent beatings of ſeditiouſly conſpiring waves: I have here contributed ſome buckets of water towards the aſſwaging of this devouring fire; ſent ſome aſſiſting neceſſaries aboard the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſinking Ship: In doing whereof, if my zeal to the Proteſtant Religion, loyalty to my Soveraign, love and fidelity to my native Country, affection and approbation of the well compoſed Lawes thereof, compaſſion and pitty to all my miſguided, miſinformed and ſeduced Country-men, ſhall expoſe me to cenſure, condemnation, nay death it ſelf, I am reſolved, by the help of God, in whom alone is my confidence, with the Apoſtle, into whatſoever condition I ſhall be caſt, therewith to remain content, eſteeming it <hi>dulce &amp; decorum pro Religione, Rege Patria legibuſque Angliae mori.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe it concerneth all who raiſe buildings, not ſo much to catch the eyes-obſervance with inſubſtantiall ſhadowes, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main laſtingly ſerviceable, to lay a ſure foundation, leaſt that decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or by oppoſing force, enforced to a removall, each particuler ſuperſtructure meet with the ſame ruine, and ſuddenly ſinking-fate: my intent therefore not being for procuration of popular ayery ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, but information and reduction of thoſe into the good old way of the Chriſtian Proteſtant Religion, Reaſon, Law and Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who through ignorance and miſinformation have been made <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115533:6"/>
inſtrumentales,</hi> the feet by which the Machiavilians of theſe times have walked on towards the end of their deſigns; <hi>manus complicantes,</hi> the hands with which Politicians have framed their Engines for an enforced alteration of <hi>Englands government;</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whoſe aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce their plots would have proved but like ſtatues without motion, or abortive Births, dead in the very womb: thoſe I mean whoſe intentions at firſt never aimed at a totall change of Government, by a diminiſhing, though in a petitiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, much leſſe a bloody compulſive way, his Majeſties royall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative and juſt Regall power; but having been abuſed through ſpecious pretences of Reformation, have been ignorant inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Englands</hi> unhappineſſe.</p>
            <p>As for the Initiatours, Contrivers, Plotters of this rooting deſign, who begin at the end thereof, and accordingly have in <hi>England, per faſque nefas,</hi> endeavoured the attaining their ends, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling all ancient bounds of Regall Prerogative, juſt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Priviledges, private mens proprieties and liberties, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſo deep in queſt of the fundamentall Lawes, that they have arrived at the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> and yet after ſix yeers endeavours, are as far from finding that fundamentall vein, as they were when their bloody deſigns opened the firſt vein in the Kingdoms body: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect a ſmooth face from them expreſſing favour to theſe lines, or remain ſatisfied with what is written, therefore I ſhall onely pray for them, that the God of heaven would open their eyes, cauſing them to ſee, how with <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> they have not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinned themſelves, but cauſed many thouſands in <hi>England</hi> to ſin, and grant them repentance and pardon for all their accumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive offences, before they go down to the grave and be ſeen no more.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore <hi>fundamina ponere,</hi> leaving diſcourſes of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a Nationall government, the antiquity, rationality and precedency of Monarchy, beyond any other form, the compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive excellency of the Engliſh Government, in reſpect of others, practized and bearing the ſame title, the Preſſe having been alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy fruitfull in Writings of that nature: lay down ſome undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble poſitions and truths, <hi>ab omnibuſque conceſſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in reſpect of a Government already lawfully ſetled.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in regard of thoſe <hi>ligamenta fidelitatis,</hi> promiſſory
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115533:7"/>
oaths, by which religious engagements we oblige our ſelves to an acknowledgement of ſome rights due to the ſupream Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, by the generally received and practized cuſtome of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as alſo to maintain ſuch rights againſt all violent oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hindering any compelled diminution or alteration of the ſame, by any perſons whomſoever.</p>
            <p>Hoping that in the reſult of all, <hi>nemo Chriſtianus contra Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, nemo Anglicina contra leges Angliae, nemo ſobrius contra rationem, nemo fidelis contra Regem, nemo Pacificus contra pacem durabilem conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det,</hi> that all true Proteſtants, rational men, faithfull Subjects, lovers of their Religion, King, Country and Peace, will condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to what hereafter they ſhall find propounded.</p>
            <p>Therefore by the way, firſt, let me requeſt all ſuch, whoſe thoughts cannot but ſpeak themſelves intereſted in theſe lines, to lay aſide all prejudicate opinions, both of my ſelf and others, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto practically different from them, prejudice being like a partition-wall, which will hinder the judgements yeelding to what is propoſed and really made good to be Reaſon, Religion and Law.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that they would baniſh from their breſts that Rebel to Religion and Reaſon, a too confident tenaciouſneſſe of their own opinions, not becauſe in their appearance they ſtill continue undoubted truths to their approving judgements; but becauſe the paſt inſinuating Declarations of ſome cunning, Polititians, and rhetoricall Jeſuitized perſwaſions of others, have conſonant to their particular erronious maximes, and pre-reſolved upon deſignes urged them to a former practice of unjuſt and unlawfull actions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, therefore that they would caſt away that deſperately ruining reſolution of <hi>potiùs malè currendo crimina criminibus addere, quàm errorem confi teri recurrendo, veritatemque veritatis cauſa propugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> being rather willing to continue ſlayes to the commiſſion of additionall ſins, then by repentance become triumphing Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, for the ſincerity of truth; when as it is far greater and better policy humane and divine, by repentance to return into the way of truth, then by a continuing progreſſe in erronious paths, to expoſe themſelves to a poſſible ruine here, and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hereafter: Beſides, the whole current of the Scriptures every
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115533:7"/>
where ſpeaketh mercy and pardon to the penitent (an argument in my judgement ſufficient to induce all thereunto againſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſuggeſtions of the world and the Devil; nay,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.21. to the end.</note> the very end of Chriſts Birth, Death, Reſurrection and Aſcention onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim an invitation of ſinners to come unto him, promiſing them pardon and ſalvation: Now therefore if that any one in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſhall turn away his ear, neglecting to hearken to the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, charm he never ſo well, let them take heed that that place of Scripture, <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6. prove not an evidence againſt their obſtinacy, and the complaint and threats of our Saviour in <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37, 38. concern not them; <hi>O Hieruſalem, Hieruſalem, which haſt killed the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them which are ſent unto thee, how often would I have gathered thee together, as a hen gathereth her chickens, and you would not: Behold therefore your habitation ſhall be left deſolate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which heavy judgement, O thou preſerver of men, keep and defend us all.</p>
            <p>But I proceed to lay down my firſt fundamentall poſitions, in reſpect of a Government already eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>That all violent and irregular alteration of Government, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the fundamentall cuſtomes and conſtitutions of every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Nation: Firſt, if it receive its original from the ſupream Magiſtrate, and preſſed upon the people, hath alwayes been brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the names of tyranny and oppeſſion; nor have ſuch ſins, (although the Word of God permit not Subjects by armes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel againſt him) paſſed unpuniſhed oftentimes here in this world; however, without repentance, cannot eſcape in the world to come.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if violently ſtreaming from the ſeditious, compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive combination of the people, without and againſt the ſupream Magiſtrates conſent, hath ever been ſtigmatized with thoſe odious titles of <hi>Rebellion and Treaſon;</hi> whoſe juſt rewards are death here, with a ſucceſſive never dying infamy, and unleſſe the mercy of Heaven interpoſe, the eternity of death hereafter.</p>
            <p>Therefore for the avoyding of Tyranny and Oppreſſion on the one ſide, preventing of Treaſon and Rebellion on the other, with all thoſe bloody iſſues and ruinous effects flowing from thence, <hi>tanquam a fonte ſanguinolento,</hi> and conſequently thoſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which <hi>tanquam undae ſequuntur undas,</hi> tread on the very heels of ſuch offences.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115533:8"/>It muſt neceſſarily be granted an undeniable truth, that obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence indiſpenſable is due from every Subject of what degree ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, according to the qualification of the perſons, unto all Lawes (not oppoſite to the Law &amp; Word of God) made &amp; confirmed by the ſupream power of any Nation; and that theſe Lawes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to reaſon, ought and muſt remain in full force and vertue, untill the ſame lawfull power, which firſt gave them the power of a commanding law, ſhall repeal and nullifie them: That all Chriſtian Subjects do or ſhould yeeld obedience to Kings perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and the Law his vertuall commands, if not derogatory to the Law of God; not onely becauſe the King, <hi>quatenus Rex,</hi> or the Law, <hi>quatenus Lex tantùm,</hi> commandeth the ſame, but becauſe in his Word he hath laid a precept upon us, both in the fourth Commandement, and in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. where he enjoyneth every ſoul to be ſubject to the higher Powers, &amp;c. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14, 15, 17. where he commandeth us by his Apoſtle, to ſubmit our ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake; whether it be unto the King, as unto the ſupream, &amp;c. ſo that if we deny active obedience to his legall commands, we deny it not to the King, and oppoſe the Law therein alone, but to God himſelf, <hi>per quem Reges regnant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 9.15, 16</note> acting contrary to his will revealed in his Word, and the practice of Chriſt himſelf, who gave <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due.</p>
            <p>But becauſe peradventure a demonſtration of my own judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment about paſſive obedience (active to Kings, having already been diſcuſſed of) may be expected, therefore that I might not leave my ſelf to the uncertain interpretation of any:</p>
            <p>I profeſſe my ſelf an Engliſh Proteſtant, and therefore in the trueſt ſenſe, ſhall not refuſe the ſtile of an Engliſh Catholike; diſavowing all hereticall, idolatrous and ſuperſtitious Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all other Opinions different from, and contradictory unto the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> eſtabliſhed in the thirty nine Articles: not becauſe it is eſtabliſhed onely, but becauſe it is conſonant and agreeable to the Word of God; the truth whereof hath been, is, and hereafter will be made good againſt all hereticall and ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall Opponents whomſoever.</p>
            <p>In particular reference to a lawfull King, and the continuance of his government in peace and piety.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115533:8"/>I deteſt and proteſt againſt all Jeſuiticall diſtinctions,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> King <hi>James</hi> premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes, and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for the Oath of Allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, pag. 50 51, 108, 109. <hi>alibique.</hi>
               </note> deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive tenents to all Religion and Government, of power reſerved in Pope or people, of what degree or number ſoever, whether they be a body <hi>repreſentative conjunctìm</hi> (if a body can properly be termed a body without an head) or any particular members <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſìm,</hi> under any pretence or intention whatſoever, by force to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of, and change the Lawes of a Kingdom, depoſe Kings, diveſt them of their lawful power, diſpenſe with Oaths, by which their Subjects ſtand as well religiouſly as naturally obliged, reſiſt their lawfull commands by the ſword, perſwading Subjects to follow their example.</p>
            <p>I acknowledge according to the truth of the Word of God,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.4. Matth. 26.51. Matth. 9.54, 55, 56. Mat. 16.23. Book of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, 3. vol. Hom. Church <hi>Engl.</hi> &amp; Artic.</note> the practice and precept of Chriſt himſelf, the examples of the Prophets and Apoſtles, the pattern of all the Martyrs, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally concurring Doctrine of the Catholike Church, now in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion continued in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That active obedience is to be yeelded to the King as ſupream <hi>in omnibus licitis,</hi> in things lawfull; but if God for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Nation ſhould ſet over us a tyrannicall King, <hi>ſecundam voluntatem pravam non rationem rectam regentem,</hi> governing by his depraved will againſt reaſon, and commanding things contrary to the Word of God, we muſt not by force of arms rebel againſt him, but rather then ſo (if not prevailing by Petition unto him, or eſcaping by flight from him) patiently ſubmit to the loſſe of our lives &amp; eſtates; agreeing with the ancient Chriſtians, that <hi>preces &amp; lachrymae ſunt arma eccleſiae,</hi> that the pen rather then the ſword, patience, prayers and tears, then actively ſhedding blood beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth Chriſtians: Herein committing my ſoul into the hands of my faithfull Creator and mercifull Redeemer,<note place="margin">Revel. 2.10. Mat. 5.10, 11, 12. 1 Pet. 3.14, 17. 1 Tim. 2.9.</note> who have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced them bleſſed that ſuffer for righteouſneſſe ſake, and the teſtimony of a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>But I know the Jeſuite and others (too neer him in opinion, though remote from him in name) will contract their browes into a frown at this (though Chriſtian like) aſſeveration and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, interpoſing many ayery ſuppoſitions, diſtinctions,<note place="margin">Homily Chur. <hi>Engl.</hi> Sacred royall Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings, printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1644.</note> and I know not what frivolous queſtions; all which I ſhall at preſent forbear to inſert, much more to anſwer; becauſe they have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently been (in the religious and rationall works of many learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115533:9"/>
Writers, both ancient and modern, refuted and made to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear but groundleſſe, quickly vaniſhing into ayre.</p>
            <p>Beſide, his royall Majeſty, ſince the beginning of this unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall War, having commanded nor demanded any thing (as in the ſequell will appear) contrary to eſtabliſhed Law, nor performed any action, which any other Prince as ſupream might not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully have done, <hi>ſe, ſobolem, leges, Regnaque defendendo:</hi> It would be a needleſſe, and a labour in vain in me (although in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience I approve the ſame) to ſpend paper in vindication of a Chriſtians paſſive obedience, it being a queſtion not ariſing from the paſt or preſent practice of our Soveraign Lord the King; therefore without all queſtion, at preſent ſtandeth not in need either of mine, or any other his Majeſties Subjects defence: For he hath been, and is ſo far from commanding any unjuſt things, contrary to the Law of God and the Land, that he hath patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffered reproaches againſt his royall perſon, deprivation of his noble Conſort, diſperſion of his Princely Son, hazard of his own life, loſſe of his Revenues, with many thouſands of his loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Subjects, nay, almoſt all the comforts which felicitates a mans life upon earth, being at laſt after all theſe a reſtrained priſoner: O happy, thrice-bleſſed wals conteyning ſuch a King, pattern of true Piety, preſident of religious conſtancy, example of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paralelled Patience! O unnaturall men! Rebels to the King, Reaſon, Religion and Law, whoſe trayterous commands thus turns Princes Pallaces into a royall Priſon: And all this he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoeth, becauſe he would govern onely by Law, and preſerve a power in himſelf, whereby he may be enabled to preſerve the Law.</p>
            <p>But I proceed, paſſing by the generall power of a King in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and in that reſpect what he may do, and conſider him onely as he is King of <hi>England,</hi> in a well ſetled Government, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to this purpoſe ſhall lay down ſome more fundamentall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and unqueſtionable truths.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> all Acts of Parliament confeſſing the 1. <hi>Jac.</hi> cap. 1. 9. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4 fol. 8</note>That our Soveraign Lord CHARLES, by the grace of God, is lawfull King of <hi>England,</hi> and of all other his Majeſties Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Countries, that he is ſupream Governour over all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and in all cauſes, whether Eccleſiaſtical or Civil.</p>
            <p>That is, There is (by the Law of the Land eſtabliſhed, in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115533:9"/>
which he is vertually preſent) no commanding power above him, without him, much leſſe againſt him; nor can, ought or muſt any <hi>conjunctim</hi> or <hi>diviſim,</hi> exerciſe any governing power within his Majeſties Dominions, nor muſt any willingly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe ſubjection or obedience to ſuch an unjuſt and uſurped power, ſtanding in oppoſition to his lawfull power.</p>
            <p>That there are <hi>regales columnae,</hi> to ſupport this Monarchicall Fabrick from ſinking or ſuffering any injury from any perſons whomſoever, as ſummoning and diſmiſſing of generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, whether Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, making or anulling of Laws, that is, his affirmative or negative voyce in Parliament; without which, the Building were rather a painted, then ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall Edifice.</p>
            <p>Secondly, making of War or Peace, that is, diſpoſing of the Militia, of arming his Subjects to prevent forraign Invaſions, or ſuppreſſe domeſtick, rebellious Inſurrections; without which it would alſo ſoon fall by ſeditious and ambitious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derminers: nor could the King without this power be able to defend himſelf from wrong, or his Subjects from oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, creating and diſpoſing of Magiſtrates, power over life and death, higheſt and laſt appeal; without which his title of Supremacy would be a title of ſupream mockery, the ſtile of<note n="*" place="margin">School boys know that <hi>Rex</hi> is but a deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative of <hi>Rego,</hi> which ſignifies to Govern.</note> 
               <hi>King</hi> a meer contradiction; nay, if he had not theſe addition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, whereby he is onely abled, <hi>Regis agere partem,</hi> he were rather <hi>Rex titularis quàm realis;</hi> and if ſo, rather <hi>regulatus;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the beſt ſenſe, but a ſupream Subject then <hi>Rex regens,</hi> by vertue of his ſupream power governing his Subjects: were he deprived of theſe neceſſary adjuncts to a regall power, he then may (as his Majeſty hath well obſerved himſelf) be waited up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bare-headed, have his hand kiſſed,<note place="margin">His Anſwer to the nineteen Propoſitions, <hi>Anno</hi> 1642.</note> his Authority declared by his Subjects; have Swords and Maces carried before him, and pleaſe himſelf with the ſight of a Crown and Scepter: but as to true and reall power, he ſhould remain but the out ſide, picture and ſign of a King.</p>
            <p>Now that all theſe, with many more attributes of power re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for a King to have, do appertain (by the eſtabliſhed Law of this Land) to our Soveraign Lord King CHARLES his Heirs and Succeſſors; I will not trouble the margin with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115533:10"/>
quotations from the Fountain,<note place="margin">Lex terrae <hi>A-1647.</hi> a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio ad fiuem. <hi>Remonſt.</hi> Feb. <hi>21. 1647.</hi> ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bique ſcriptis.</note> to make good, but refer the Reader to thoſe pure ſtreams flowing from thence, thoſe brief Collections of that Reverend Lawyer Judge <hi>Jenkins,</hi> who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Atlas</hi> like, hath ſupported the true fundamentall Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> and like a faithfull Expoſitor, given the moſt religious, rationall and lawfull practiced ſenſe of them.</p>
            <p>But for the cleering hereof, I ſhall propound ſome queries to all rationall men, which will (the premiſes conſidered) anſwer of themſelves, to which even the knowledge of the meaneſt judgement, if he know any thing, cannot but aſſent as reall truth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Preſuppoſed the King not the King in his minority, although it is as true then, for there is his tacite ſupream power impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jenk.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtr. <hi>Febr.</hi> 21. 1647. <hi>Vide Recordi.</hi>
               </note>Whether ever in this Kingdom any new Law was enjoyned or new Oath impoſed upon the people in oppoſition to the Law eſtabliſhed; by the two houſes <hi>conjunctim,</hi> or by either of them <hi>ſeperatim,</hi> without, nay, againſt the King's conſent; and if none, as none can be produced, by what power have they contrived Ordinances, and impoſed them with a Vow and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, ſolemn League and Covenant, contrary to eſtabliſhed Law, and his Majeſties Proclamation?</p>
            <p>Whether or no, turbulent, violent and irregular tranſaction in former Parliaments, wherein Kings have been depoſed or neceſſitated to unlawfull condeſcentions, through force or fear have not been by ſucceeding Parliaments made null, and thoſe Parliaments themſelves eſteemed but as traiterous Aſſemblies: and ſo, as cannot be denied, <hi>Res pares cum paribus comparemus;</hi> And let us all pray, that <hi>England</hi> may enjoy the happineſſe of a free, lawfully acting, Chriſtian like, peaceable, unbyaſed, no private ſelf ends reſpecting, but the truly publike and generall good, cordially affecting, and really effecting Parliament, To which let all true Engliſh men, with my ſelf ſay, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether ever formerly the Lords and Commons <hi>conjunctim,</hi> or either of them <hi>diviſim,</hi> had the diſpoſing of the Militia of the Kingdom, did create Magiſtrates, had power over life and death, to whom higheſt and laſt appeal were made, did make a great Seal, acting by vertue thereof, by any Law of the Land eſtabliſhed, without, nay againſt the King's conſent? And if there be no Law extant, intereſting them in ſuch a power, but on the contrary, it muſt neceſſarily be confeſſed, that all theſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115533:10"/>
things (by the letter of the Law, and the continuall practice thereof, which is <hi>optimus leges interpres</hi>) do belong to the King's Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors: their own Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of the ſecond of <hi>June,</hi> 1642. confeſſing no leſſe;<note place="margin">Firſt Book Col. Ordnan. 307.</note> for then they petitioned him for a reſignation of all theſe <hi>inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia regalia,</hi> for the removing of fears and jealouſies between him and his people; which muſt neceſſarily imply a tacite confeſſion, that his Majeſty is ſolely intereſted in the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them; for to what end ſhould they petition for thoſe things, which without his conſent they may claim as their own: and if ſo, let every mans judgement ſpeak, <hi>Quis reus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether or no there be any Law remaining eſtabliſhed, or any clauſe reſerved in the Law, by vertue whereof the Lords and Commons, or either of them are authorized in any caſe whatſoever reall, much leſſe upon a pretence of any caſe, to remove Counſellours from his Majeſty by force, to impriſon his ſacred Perſon, to uſe the regall Power, to alter the Lawes eſtabliſhed, to impoſe new Lawes without his conſent upon his Subjects, and the like, by force: All which, and more then theſe, have been put in practice ſince theſe unhappy times began; and if they cannot produce any Law, or the leaſt reſemblance of a Law, nay, of Chriſtian reaſon, to warrant ſuch like actions,<note place="margin">Judge <hi>Jenkins Lex t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rrae</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monffr. <hi>Frb.</hi> 1647.</note> they muſt give us leave to ask the queſtion, <hi>Who are guilty of Treaſon?</hi> ſeeing all theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars thus uſurped, are by the Law declared no leſſe.</p>
            <p>And here by the way, let me put them in mind of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent judgement of former Ages, in Biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Martyr for our Religion, from ſuch kind of poſitions or practices.</p>
            <p>He would not admit of the Popes authority in <hi>England,</hi> becauſe he was pre-engaged to the King by Oath,<note place="margin">Book Martyrs</note> according to the Law of the Land; affirming, that the Popes authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was againſt the Crown, Cuſtome, and Lawes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: Now unleſſe there be a Law authorizing the People, under what notion ſoever, to do that which was unlawfull in the Pope to do (the offence being one and the ſame, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115533:11"/>
only by differing perſons) I know not what to write more, but that Pope and People begin both with one letter; praying God to deliver us from the Pope and Papiſtical falſe Doctrines.</p>
            <p>As for that old ſtalking-horſe, the fundamental Law, which hath ſo often and ſo long been pretended, as an undeniable warrant, authorizing their beginnings and proceedings in oppoſition to his Majeſty: Truly loyall Engliſh hearts and rationall men will no ſooner credit that there is ſuch a Law, becauſe of their meer declarative affirmation, then that there is ſuch an one as <hi>Atlas,</hi> really ſupporting the Heavens with his ſhoulders, becauſe Poets have delivered ſo much to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages, in their feigned writings.</p>
            <p>There indeed not any ſuch Law, warranting theſe kind of actions, for none hitherto hath appeared in view; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a maxime, that <hi>quod non apparet jure non eſt;</hi> therefore ſhall be bold to put them in mind of part of Maſter <hi>Pym's</hi> ſpeech at the beginning of this Parliament, leaving the application to their conſideration.</p>
            <p>The Law is that which putteth a difference between good and evill, between juſt and unjuſt; if you take away the Law all things will fall into a confuſion, every man will become a Law to himſelf; which in the depraved condition of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature, muſt needs produce many great enormities: Luſt will become a Law, Envy will become a Law, Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will become a Law; and what dictates and deciſions ſuch Lawes will produce, may eaſily be diſcerned. Thus far Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Pym.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that theſe things may not come to paſſe in its height however, and perfection in theſe our dayes: Let us pray, that the Lord would grant us all grace to tread conſtant ſteps in the path of his Law, giving us loyall hearts to the King, and cauſing us to expreſſe a reall, not verball obedience to the Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>Further, becauſe <hi>humanum eſt errare,</hi> and <hi>omnis perfectio noſtra eſt imperfectio;</hi> all of us being full of originall ſin; by reaſon of which, the ſuggeſtion of Satan, and the enticing pleaſures
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115533:11"/>
and profits of this life, we are alas (<hi>quamvis Christiani,</hi> though ſtiled Chriſtians) yet ready to commit ſin with greedineſſe againſt the God of heaven; as alſo, too too apt to prefer our own private advantage and intereſt before the publike good and benefit, not minding the peoples happineſſe in practiſing piety, and enjoying Peace the mother of plenty, but often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, ſpurred on by avaritious and ambitiouſly aſpiring thoughts; we neglect rendring to God his, and all other degrees of men, from the Prince to the meaneſt of the people, their reſpective dues, which often occaſioneth that confuſion, like a fierce torrent overfloweth, and ruine like a boiſterous ſtorme, ſuddenly ſhipwracks a well governed Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Therefore are Oathes <hi>tanquam Clavi religioſi,</hi> framed to keepe this building of Government more firme and cloſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: To this end the Oathes of Alleagiance and Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy are by the Law of the Land injoyned to be taken by all Perſons capable thereof, eſpecially men imployed in any publicke Office, but more particularly the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament, <hi>ſine quo non eſt talis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In which they ſweare without Equivocation or mentall reſervation, to beare Faith and true alleagiance to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie his Heires and Succeſſours, to defend him and them againſt all Conſpiracies and attempts whatſoever againſt their Perſons, Crown and Dignitie.</p>
            <p>Now let all reaſonable Men conſider, and within their owne judgements reſolve theſe queſtions themſelves.<note place="margin">Coll. Ordn. firſt book, 93.</note> Is it maintenance of his Majeſties crown and dignity, and defence againſt all attempts, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To force the <hi>Militia</hi> inſeperably belonging to the Crown from him, under pretence of groundleſſe feares and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies.</p>
            <p>Is it maintenance of his Crowne and Dignitie,<note place="margin">Firſt book Coll. Par. Ordn. pag. 309, 310. <hi>June</hi> 1642.</note> I meane his regall Crowne of Government to demand, as they did, in their nineteen Propoſitions, all governing Kingly power from him; plainly then ſpeaking, that their intent was not to maintaine (notwithſtanding their glorious pretences)
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115533:12"/>
the Law, nor reſolution <hi>ad errores reformandum,</hi> but <hi>regimen Angliae mutandum.</hi> For had they really intended as they ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bally often pretended in their Ordinances and Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Coll. Ordn- 130. <hi>alibique.</hi>
               </note> Preſervation of the Law of the Land, his Majeſties royall perſon,<note place="margin">Fo. 15. Coll. Ordn. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1641.</note> honour and Eſtate, juſt Prerogative and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty; they ſhould have provided (having alſo declared in that grand Remonſtrance to the Kingdome, that their intent was to reſtore the ancient honour, greatneſſe and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Crowne.) More wals of Braſſe, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to invent (which I muſt confeſſe paſſeth my beleefe) more, and a more excellent one, for preventing any more ſhaking of the Law eſtabliſhed, by intrenching upon the Kings juſt Prerogative and the Subjects Liberty, then the Trienniall Parliament, which they confeſſe themſelves to be a perpetuall Spring of remedies for the future. And not on the firſt Onſet, <hi>Magis Poſtulare quam Petere,</hi> totally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire rather then deſire the Kings royall Power;<note place="margin">Nineteen Propoſ.</note> for that end breaking all hedges of publicke and generall liberty to preſerve or advantage ſome few private peeces of incloſed grounds.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagiance and Supremacy.</note>Is it faith and alleagiance, and a Declaration in your Conſciences, that none hath power to diſcharge Subjects from their Alleagiance and Obedience to his Majeſty?</p>
            <p>To frame Oathes wherein you ingage your fellow Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,<note place="margin">Coll. Ordn. 93, 138.</note> even in a manner to proteſt againſt their alleagiance and obedience to his Majeſtie; by Covenanting to aſſiſt the Forces raiſed and continued by both Houſes, who are but Subjects (elſe why doe they Petition to his Majeſty in thoſe ſubmiſſive ſtiles, Of his Majeſties moſt humble and loyall Subjects) againſt the Forces raiſed by the King; and that they ſhall nor directly nor indirectly aſſiſt the Forces raiſed by the King, without the conſent of both Houſes; witneſſe their Vow and Covenant, Ordered <hi>die Sabbathi</hi> 1643. and and their latter compoſed Negative Oath, much to the ſame effect.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy.</note>Is it a Declaration in your Conſcience, that the Kings highneſſe is the onely ſupreame Governour of this Realme,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115533:12"/>
and all other his Majeſties Dominions. To deprive him of his Negative voyce in Parliament, to create Magiſtrates, to exerciſe a power over the life and death of his Subjects, nay to doe any thing, but what Subjects ought to doe, and Oaths oblige unto?</p>
            <p>Is it a defence of all Juriſdictions and Priviledges, Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minences and Authorities belonging to the Kings highneſſe, his heirs and Succeſſours, and annexed to the imperiall crown of this Realm?</p>
            <p>To declare that the King is not in a condition to govern,<note place="margin">Anſwer to the <hi>Scots</hi> Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 28. 1647.</note> to impriſon him, to affirm that they will make no more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes unto him, that they will ſettle the government of the Kingdom without and againſt him?</p>
            <p>Theſe conſidered, I appeal to all: hear O heaven, judge O earth, with yee Inhabitants of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> who are guilty of perjury? I am ſure none but will confeſſe that the Oaths of Alleagiance and Supremacy are lawfull in themſelves, commanded by a compleatly lawfull authority, remaining enjoyned &amp; confirmed by act of Parliament, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought to be taken by all, according to the literall ſenſe thereof, and endeavours uſed to perform the ſame, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to each mans uttermoſt ability.</p>
            <p>As for that exception ſavouring more of a Turkiſh or Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiticall, then of a Chriſtian Proteſtant's affirmative judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nay, it is contrary to common reaſon, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vain.</p>
            <p>For any one to apprehend, that ſingular perſons one by one, are obliged to the obſervation of theſe Oaths, but a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy repreſentative is one; as if one man alone could be perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and yet that the multiplication of that unite (equally engaged both in the keeping and the breach thereof) to four hundred, gave a diſpenſation from the guiltineſſe of the ſin, as if an offender were an offender, becauſe <hi>quatenus homo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus per ſe peccans,</hi> ſinning as one man alone; and not becauſe the offence committed was a deviation from the Law of God, Reaſon or the Law; when as it is far more correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to reaſon, to affirm that the more the Offenders are, the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115533:13"/>
more guilty, becauſe more ſpreading; and the greater the Offenders are, as repreſentitave bodies, or Magiſtrates abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a conferred power are more dangerous, becauſe exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary, for <hi>citius ducti per exempla quàm praecepta,</hi> we are too apt to follow ſin in a multitude, eſpecially if they be great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of repute, pretending aſſertours and reformers, though they prove deſertours and deformers of Religion, Lawes and Liberties. Beſides, God in the Scriptures commandeth us not to follow a multitude to do evil, which implieth that a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude may do evil; and what is a repreſentitative body but a multitude, in a grammaticall ſenſe, and therefore if they do evil, they muſt not be followed: Nay, the whole current of Gods Word runs with variety of judgements threatned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all that are in authority, if they recede from his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. The Prophet <hi>Micah,</hi> with others, are full in this reſpect,<note place="margin">You may ſee many more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</note> 
               <hi>Micah</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>Amos</hi> 6.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5.9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. O come therefore for the prevention of ſuch like judgements, and the removing from us what we already lye under, let us by a timely repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, return unto the God of heaven, humbly entreating him that he would forgive us all our ſins; more particularly that he would not lay this hainous ſin of Perjury to <hi>Englands</hi> charge, but give us grace to mourn and weep for that, and all others which have occaſioned our Land to mourn in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and weep in blood.</p>
            <p>Now to contract the premiſed ſeverals into a narrower compaſſe, thereby to make this rooting deſign appear plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all.</p>
            <p>I ſhall deſire all rationall men to take notice, that the Lords and Commons in that grand Remonſtrance to the Kingdom, in <hi>December</hi> 1641. and their Petitions to his Majeſtie, Declarations and Ordinances, Preambles to their Proteſtation, Vow and Covenant, ſolemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which were but as ſo many applications to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for their information and procuration of their approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions aſſiſtance and affections; alwayes pretended a preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kings Honour, Rights and Authority, the Law
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115533:13"/>
of the Land, the Proteſtant Religion, the Liberty and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of the Subject. To this purpoſe you ſhall find many expreſſions.</p>
            <p>In the grand Remonſtrance they complain of the Jeſuited Papiſts, &amp;c. and a malignant Party,<note place="margin">Col. Ordnan. fo 3.</note> pernicious deſigns to ſubvert the fundamentall Lawes and principles of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, on which the Religion and juſtice of this Kingdom is eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>They confeſſe the King to be truſted with the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical law, as well as temporall,<note place="margin">Coll. Ordn. fo. 19.</note> that next under God the people owe obedience unto him.</p>
            <p>They profeſſe, their intent was not to aboliſh all go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and leave every man to his own fancy, for the ſervice and worſhip of God, but to reduce within bounds the exorbitant power which ſome Prelates had aſſumed to themſelves, contrary to the Word of God, and law of the land.</p>
            <p>Where by the way takes notice, that then there was no mention made of extirpating Epiſcopall Government, ſince that, as much as in them lyeth, by their ſolemn League and Covenant, and Ordinances effected.</p>
            <p>They profeſſe to maintain the true Proteſtant Religion,<note place="margin">Coll. Ordn. 281.</note> the Kings juſt Prerogative, the lawes and liberties of the Land, and the priviledges of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Reſolved upon the Queſtion,<note place="margin">12. July 1642 fo. 457.</note> 
               <hi>That an Army ſhall be forthwith raiſed for the ſafety of the Kings perſon, preſerving of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Lawes, Liberties and Peace of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There they expreſſe fears,<note place="margin">Fo. 461.</note> that the true Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Lawes will be extinguiſhed, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That they will maintain and ſupport his Majeſties royall Honour and greatneſſe.<note place="margin">Fo. 466.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But I will trouble the Reader with no more expreſſions of this nature; the firſt Book of collection of Ordinances, if he pleaſe, will afford him variety.</p>
            <p>Take a brief view of their Preambles to all their Oaths,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115533:14"/>
which they pretend as motives and grounds occaſioning their framing and impoſing them.</p>
            <q>
               <p>May 5. 1641.</p>
               <p>We the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c. having cauſe to ſuspect endeavours ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing to ſubvert the true reformed Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in his Majeſties Dominions<note n="*" place="margin">Obſerve that <hi>Establiſhed.</hi>
                  </note> eſtabliſhed, and the fundamentall Lawes, and to introduce an arbitrary and tyrannicall Government, &amp;c. therefore make this enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proteſtation &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>June 1643. in their Vow and Covenant.</p>
               <p>There they declare, <hi>That there hath been, and is a Popiſh and traiterous Plot for the ſubverſion of the true Proteſtant Religion, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Thus you may perceive how in all their applications to the common people, they ſtill urge intentions of preſerving the King's juſt Prerogative and royall Rights, true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, the Lawes and Liberties of the Land: Now this muſt neceſſarily, according to common ſenſe, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued by the common people (whatſoever private reſerved reſolutions to the contrary, the framers of the Oathes and Ordenances had to themſelves) a preſervation and defence of Religion, Prerogatives, Rights, Lawes and Liberties, which are eſtabliſhed and in being; for according to that old adage, <hi>ex nihilo nil fit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas, theſe ſpecious pretences were but Decoyes ſent abroad to catch the plain hearted people, and the leſſe advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed multitude into a complying aſſiſtance; their hands and tongues muſt help toward the demolition of <hi>England's</hi> anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and well compacted Monarchical Fabrick; their breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115533:14"/>
bodies muſt be inſtrumentall piles, to mount theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigners into the chair of a new modelized, pre-intended Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe therefore (contrary to all their Paper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligencers,<note place="margin">Nineteen Propoſitions.</note> daily diiſperſed among the people) they in their firſt Propoſitions to his Majeſty (as I have already obſerved) lay the foundation, though cunningly, of this generall alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in Church and State, wherein they had left nothing more to demand of him, but that (as a King, he had nothing more to grant.)</p>
            <p>Which deſign of theirs hath appeared in more legible, additionall demands in their ſucceeding Treaties and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, from that time unto this very day, wherein they have violently deprived his Majeſty of his regall power; he at preſent being ſo far from commanding as a * King,<note place="margin">Being kept as a Priſoner in the Iſle of <hi>Wight.</hi>
               </note> that his power in commanding is far below the commanding power of ſome of his meaneſt Subjects: <hi>Proh dolor! uſque quo domine uſque quò;</hi> how long, Lord, how long, holy and true, wilt thou ſuffer the Rod of the wicked to remain upon the back of the righteous? how long ſhall the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity triumph, ſpeaking fiercely, ſmiting down thy people and troubling thy Heritage? Deliver our Soveraign thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant King CHARLES from cruell men, who imagine evil things in their heart, making war continually; whoſe tongues are ſharper then a Serpent, and under whoſe lips lye the poyſon of Adders, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, to make theſe Rooters deſign appear plainer and plainer to every eye, the Treaties at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and ſince at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> (at which time nothing was left ungranted by his Majeſty, whereby his people might be ſatisfied) but that he would have ſomething left, I ſay, as King, to give; will evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence it to any impartiall judgement.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Oxford, Anno</hi> 1643. the maine diſpute betweene his Majeſtie and the two Houſes Commiſſioners was, who ſhould have the Power of Nomination and Election of State-Officers. The Right to both belonged to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115533:15"/>
how ever, ſo deſirous was he of Peace and a Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation (his heart bleeding in tenderneſſe within, for the loſſe of ſo much of his Subjects blood) did readily and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly condeſcend that the Power of Nomination ſhould be theirs, reſerving choice of them to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now let us weigh the inequality, in reference to the prevention of the effuſion of more blood. It may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon grounds of reaſon, that if I have the Power of Nomination, I will not name any one in whom I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not confidently repoſe my truſt, and of whom I have not a good opinion; therefore, if it be onely Peace and a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall agreement betweene two differing Parties, where it is ſometimes fitting that both ſhould abate of the rigour of their demands, what need I care who chooſeth, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom the election falleth, ſeeing they are all equall in my eſteeme: But this would not doe; they muſt have the Kings Supremacy, Election too, all, or as yet no peace; otherwiſe indeed the Civill Government cannot be alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from a Monarchy into an Ariſtocracy; and ſo by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ſubdivide it ſelfe into a Democracy. The Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall cannot be changed from Epiſcopacy into Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and ſo againe into Independency or confuſion; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly at this day ſo appearing. Whereas if theſe men pre-intended not theſe things, but had really intended Peace, or reſented the then bleeding condition and ruining King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England,</hi> they would not ſurely have ſtood upon ſuch unneceſſary punctilioes, not any way abſolutely availe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the generall good of the Nation; though abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary Rights belonging to his Majeſty, with which he could neither in Honour, Juſtice, or Conſcience voluntarily part. O Lord forgive them, forgive them ſuch their unreaſonable and unſeaſonable Demands, and lay not to their charge thoſe ſeverall bloudy iſſues which (ſince that time) have guſh'd out in many places of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, let us take notice of the further progreſſe, for <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115533:15"/>
repente fit turpiſſimus,</hi> of theſe deſtructive Engeneers.</p>
            <p>Hath not his Majeſtie reſigned all his regall Power, ſince that, unto the two Houſes during his life, being onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous that his royall Children may receive no prejudice by his too gracious condiſcentions, freely offering a generall Pardon, and an Act of Oblivion to every one. Yet this will not ſatisfie them; they muſt have him forfeit his Honour and Reaſon, by acknowledging himſelfe the Fountaine and originall cauſe of their unnaturally ſhedding of his Subjects blood; (ſtrange action, that the gulty Offenders muſt be juſtified, and the Offended guiltleſſe deſired unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to condemne themſelves) and wound his Conſcience by pulling upon himſelfe and Poſterity that eating ſinne of Sacriledge, by aſſenting unto an utter Extirpation of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopall government, and a devaſtation of the Churches patrimony, contrary to his Oath taken at his Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Thus ſtill you ſee the Deſigne of theſe Rooters at firſt, was to alter the Government of this Kingdome; and to that end have to deprive his Majeſtie of his regall Power,<note place="margin">Fo. 20, 34, 30, 33.</note> which ſince hath been openly avowed in their Declaration concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Scots</hi> Papers 13. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1647.</p>
            <p>But peradventure, ſome will ſay that they are zealous ſupporters of the Subjects Liberties, and quellers of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed actions, as Swearing, immoderate drinking, breaking of the Sabboth, and the like.</p>
            <p>To which I returne an anſwer in generall, that nothing can be more deſired, either for the ſuppreſſing or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all ſinfull words and deeds, and all ſuch viciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guilty Perſons; or conducing to the liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juct; if men deſire onely to enjoy liberty under a Law, and not live as libertines without a Government than what was eſtabliſhed and confirmed by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before ever they expoſed their grand Remonſtrance, that ſeede Plott of — to the view of the World;<note place="margin">Decemb. 1641</note> witneſſe that Declaration it ſelfe, which recounteth ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115533:16"/>
Acts of favour condeſcended unto by his Majeſtie for the Subjects benefit; which with that laſting Bulwarke of preventing or remedying Errours, the Trienniall Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, were enough to ſatisfie any but ſeditious and ambitiouſly aſpiring thoughts. To make this appeare, It is worthy obſervation, that after the iſſuing out of that Remonſtrance, not one Propoſition was ever tendered to his Majeſtie, really tending to the generall good and liberty of every Subject; but whatſoever were preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him under the title of Propoſitions, contained nothing but Demands, <hi>in ordine ad Cauſam,</hi> in order to this Deſigne of alteration and change of Government. Now at this very day (as every one not prepoſſeſſed with prejudice, cannot but grant) the viſible purchaſe of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, Perjury, blood and oppreſſion; an ill foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the worſt lime to erect a building with, and which moſt commonly is followed with ſucceeding heavy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;<note place="margin">Micah 3.9, 10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>From which good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this purpoſe further; you have already ſeene Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances framed, Oathes contrived for the Eradication of Epiſcopall government; and leaſt it ſhould by degrees, like a Flower preſſed downe by the violence of a falling ſhowre, riſe againe in future times, when more favourable ſunny dayes appear, they have expoſed to Sale its Lands, the Churches patrimony.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen the Presbyterian Government alſo digeſted into Ordinances, the preaching of it into approbation, the practice of it in ſeverall Churcher in <hi>London,</hi> and other adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent parts, the peoples obedience preſſed thereunto by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the preſent Synod.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen the civill Government alſo changed, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of one or both houſes ſupplying the place of Acts of Parliament, without the Royall aſſent; Demands of a totall reſignation of his Majeſties regall Power; and becauſe not in every reſpect condeſcended unto (as what father will be ſo unjuſt to his Poſterity, though he may be uncharitable to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115533:16"/>
himſelf, as to deprive them of their Inheritance, contrary to the Law of Nature, Religion and Law) the King therefore detained a Priſoner.</p>
            <q>Tantumne poteſt ſuadere malorum religio!</q>
            <p>Thus you may ſee the Deſigners riding triumphantly in the bloody Chariot of their compaſſed Ends, Revelling it at the Helmes of the Church and State, whileſt their Royall injured Maſter is forced to a ſad Cabbin under decks.</p>
            <p>O that my abuſed Country-Men would ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Premiſes, and that they would at length deſert theſe Impoſtors, who by their glorious pretences of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, have deceived them into a Ruining aſſiſtance of themſelves and others; not thinking it a ſhame to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe an errour, and return when their Judgements are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that their former Judgements and practiſes have been erronious.</p>
            <p>Againe, you have ſeene the meanes uſed by them to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect their ends; by Perjury, infringing their Oathes of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagiance, Supremacy, and their owne famed Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the effuſion of Blood. And here I cannot chooſe but adde my feares, that ſome tall and gloriouſly ſpreading Cedars of Church and State, have rather beene hewen downe, becauſe they hindered the Proſpect of others, or prejudiced the riſing growth of ſome Neighbour ſhrubs than fallen becauſe rotten, uſeleſſe or cumberſome to the grounds; which if true, (as ſome in the world beſt know) we had all need to pray that the Lord would even in the blood of Chriſt Jeſus waſh this Nation, eſpecially from ſuch kinde of blood-guiltineſſe.</p>
            <p>You may read the ſad effects of theſe Deſignes, A wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed King in diſtreſſe; A diſcontented Nobilitie; A diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate and diſperſed Gentry; A diſgraced diſparaged and defamed Orthodox Cleargy; A murmuring and repining
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115533:17"/>
Communalty; An impoveriſhed Countrey; A ſelfe-diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring Nation, Diviſion, Ambition, Sedition and Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the forerunners of a generall ruine and deſolation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Helpe O Lord leaſt we periſh;</hi> And it be ſaid of us, What is become of that glory of Nations, <hi>England?</hi> formerly fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and beloved by all, yet not for feare expreſſing love to any, leaſt what was omce ſpoken of <hi>Troy,</hi> be affirmed true of our Kingdome
<q>Jam ſeges eſt ubi Anglia fuit.</q>
            </p>
            <p>You may every where ſee God diſhonoured, the Church of God unfrequented; Schiſmes and Prophaneneſſe every where abounded, and Hereſies of all ſorts, even to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of the Deity of Chriſt, the holy Scriptures, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the ſoule, and all theſe if not publiquely main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, yet connived at by thoſe who pretend otherwiſe; you may ſee all Religion contracted into tongue diſcourſe, Sanctification ſwallowed up by Juſtification; as if becauſe Chriſt dyed to ſave Sinners, we muſt therefore wilfully ſinne if we will be ſaved; you have many running ſo farre from the Papiſts meritorious hope of gaining heaven by good Workes, that they expect in haſte to poſt thither by a barren Faith; arguing, nay eſteeming good Workes as altogether unneceſſary; when as indeed they muſt both be concomitants; for ſuch a Faith without Workes will prove but a lame Sacrifice; and Workes without Faith will be but a blinde Offering, never finde the way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>You may ſee <hi>London,</hi> an envyed City, declined in the affections of all abroad,<note place="margin">By aſſeſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, &amp;c.</note> becauſe they were blinded in their affections by theſe deceivers at home, who by degrees have eaten out the very heart of her Honour, Wealth and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115533:17"/>You have ſeen many of her Citizens toſſed too and fro with every winde of Doctrine, ſteering their courſe with the current of each prevailing Faction, rather yeelding to a deſtruction, then endeavouring a preſervation of the Cities honour and wealth.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen her well proportioned and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Government daſhed in pieces, the wiſdom of ſome of her wiſe men degenerated into a ſelf-contriving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Advantage, neglecting the Cities good in generall.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen her grand Counſell turned into a Counſell of War, combining with the unruly Sword, to diſturb, nay to deſtroy the Inhabitants with her civill Government; many ſacrificing their fellow-Citizens, to the diſpoſall of domineering Faction: ſpirits who eat the bread of extortion,<note place="margin">Prov. 4.17.</note> and drink the wine of violence.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen the Cities peace, (formerly even to the envy of their Neighbours, dwelling onely within her walls) whileſt blood, want and poverty ran like a devouring Lyon up and down each Country) inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by thoſe who had moſt reaſon to preſerve it in peace.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen Sword-men, ſtrangers unto you (if you conſider your ſelves as Citizens of that famous Metropolis) by ſome ſtiled your ſervants, becauſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained and paid you; but howſoever, I ſay, not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115533:18"/>
to the City, but more truely ſervants to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious vipers within the City, even glorying in dying the ſtones of your ſtreets with your own childrens blood.</p>
            <p>Nay conſider, I appeal to the whole City, what practicall Law have you almoſt left now in uſe, but the Law of impriſonment, whereby ſome men (firſt being made pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endly guilty of that old ayery bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear crime, ill affection, or if you will, that beldam fault malignancy, that is, that will not ſwim in the ſame current of ſuch hainous ſins with the faction) are (to uſe their own word) ſecured; or others by reaſon of their long continuing diſtractions, being diſabled ſo fully and ſpeedily to ſatisfie ſome griping Creditors their debts, are the ſooner haſtened by additionall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, want and grief, to a ſatisfaction of the laſt debt they owe to nature in a loathſom priſon.</p>
            <p>Or elſe, that (in it ſelf excellent) but (as it is now uſed) bloody lettered Law, for ſuppreſſing and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing pretended mutinies, which only like a Gy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, ſtandeth armed at the door, that ſo each ſucceſſive Faction may the more freely ruine within; in the mean time, denying the entrance either of juſtice, mercy, peace or truth.</p>
            <p>You have long ſince ſeen the Pulpit from whence nothing but the ſincerity of truth, religious admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, holy advice, perſwaſively tending to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of godlineſſe and true righteouſneſſe ſhould iſſue forth, turned into a ſophiſticall Desk, to diſtract the brains of men with ſtrange diſtinctions of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, new fangled Doctrine, perſwading their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115533:18"/>
perſons and Eſtates to an aſſiſting compliance in the late Wars.</p>
            <p>You have heard bitter expreſſions there againſt the eſtabliſhed Government of the Kingdom, ſome envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like mad, more more then rationall men, much leſſe Chriſtians againſt Epiſcopacy as Antichriſtian, and the book of Common Prayer as unlawfull and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious, their beſt arguments being but invective rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; although one hath ſtood the ſhock unmoved of the moſt fiery opponents, and the other a perfect pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of true Piety, both of them receiving approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and applauſe from all other Proteſtant Churches beyond the Seas, being onely diſgraced and defamed, though without juſt cauſe, at home, by children of her owne womb.</p>
            <p>You have heard the Ceremonies of the Church ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led limbs of Antichriſt, and others perſwaded that they were impoſed on tender conſciences as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; whenas indeed their own conſciences could not but inform them the contrary, and that they were onely ordained for order and decency ſake.</p>
            <p>Beſides,<note place="margin">His Majeſties Anſwer to the Kingdoms Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1641.</note> if any one ſeemed offenſive to tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, his Majeſty (long before the Sword was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheathed) graciouſly promiſed an exemption from obſervance of them, and therefore needed not to have been made Arguments perſwading to blood.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen learned Divines, Doctor <hi>Featly,</hi> that brazen wall of our Religion, who unrazed, hath main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his hold, retorting the Jeſuites arrowes into their own breſts with ſhamefull wounds: Doctor
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115533:19"/>
               <hi>Holſworth,</hi> a lively pattern of Piety: with many other religious and learned Divines, impriſoned and diſgraced.</p>
            <p>And my dear Country-men, <hi>ad quem finem haec om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> to what end think you did all theſe things tend? Pray conſider, you may ſee the reſult of all quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in what concerneth you to whom I write, I meane you miſled inſtruments, for I intend not (as I have already written) the contrivers hereof no further then as I am a Chriſtian to pray for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, converſion and forgiveneſſe.</p>
            <p>You have been pleaſed, like children, in lieu of things ſubſtantiall, with toyes, as pulling down of May-poles, deſtruction of ſenſeleſſe ſtony croſſes, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Tavern ſigns by fantaſticall cringers inſerted inſtead of Angels pictured; I think leaſt the ſight of ſuch ſhadowes ſhould put the miſled people in minde of thoſe reall Angels in heaven, and thereby fright or invite them into a too ſoon repentance.</p>
            <p>You have had as fruits of your endeavoured Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, ignorant painted glaſſe windowes broken, the Communion-table removed, the Font locally chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, though as by Baptiſme we are viſibly initiated into the Chriſtian Congregation, it more ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantly became the entrance into, then the body of the materiall Church, yet neither of them ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely and meerly neceſſary, as to counterpoize blood.</p>
            <q>Heu pro quantillo pacem perdidimus.</q>
            <p>You have had a new Directory, a piece made like
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115533:19"/>
wax, apted for any impreſſion, eaſily ſqueezed into any form by active brains.</p>
            <p>You have had a Catechiſme in a large Character, the iſſue of above ſix yeers labour; which ever ſince King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt's dayes, you might have fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed your ſelves with, in a ſmaller print, at an eaſie rate.</p>
            <p>And to knit all theſe together, you have the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government practized in place and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Epiſcopall, and what have you purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by this? onely an intermixture of Lay-men with the Clergy (as afterward I ſhall plainly make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear) for the managing of Eccleſiaſticall affairs, both concerning Doctrine and Diſcipline.</p>
            <q>Heu pro quàm parvis tantum ſanguinis effudimus!</q>
            <p>Thus much I write (God the ſearcher of all hearts is my witneſſe) not to revile any Divines of the Presbyterian Party, whom I honour as Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours from Heaven, when they diſpenſe the truth of of God's Word: but they muſt give me leave to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint them, that unleſſe they can ſhew any better grounds then I have hitherto read or heard from any of them ſince theſe unnaturall Wars, for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good the lawfulneſſe of introducing this their meer alteration of Government by blood, contrary to the Kings conſent, and the warrant of the Law of the Land, and having not the leaſt ground for it in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115533:20"/>
the Word of God: No errours formerly in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment being unreformed by his Majeſty, no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full means by a Synoy legally called and elected for redreſſe of what poſſibly could be found either unneceſſary or burdenſome in the Church to really tender conſciences, being by him alſo denied; the Poynt of Government being then onely, and ſtill is the difference between his Majeſty and the two Houſes; Therefore although the Proteſtants and they mutually agree in the fundamentals ef faith, and many other neceſſary truthes; yet I ſay, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but certifie them, that neither my ſelf, nor any Proteſtant of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> have reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that they have kept ſo cloſe to the rule of God's Word, Reaſon and the Law, as they ſhould have done,<note place="margin">Malachi 2.7.</note> or perhaps may prend. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p>If they have any Arguments now in this juncture of time, beſides that of meerly ignorant perſons profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of their good intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; good meaning, which they know will not excuſe a <hi>toto,</hi> though in ſome things in may a <hi>tanto.</hi> It being a common excuſe of many in theſe times, though they ſtill perſiſt in their irregularly, firſt begun courſes, they may perform a Chriſtian like and wiſe duty to themſelves for their owne vindication, and to others, for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, to divulge them to the world; or if they cannot produce any, that then they would be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded even for Chriſt Jeſus ſake, the Biſhop of our ſoules, to returne and doe their firſt workes, leaſt God come againſt them and us, and remove our
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115533:20"/>
Candleſtick out of its place. But I proceed:</p>
            <p>Becauſe the introduction of the Presbyterian go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the Church, and a proportionable alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Civill Government in the State is by ſome Miniſters of that Party cryed up as the <hi>unum neceſſarium,</hi> tending to their preintended Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the fulfilling of their ſolemne League and Covenant; I ſhall endeavour (although the Deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners intents probably were to lock faſt the Common Peoples Conſciences thereby unto them) to make good, according to the rule of Reaſon, Religion and Law, that nothing leſſe is comprehended and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein; ſo that none ſtand ingaged, unleſſe they wilfully will perſiſt in ſin, by their further aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to endeavour a compleating of their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe I ſhall deſire all a little to reflect backe upon what I have already promiſed; how that ſeeing the irregular faction of the two Houſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes applyed themſelves to the Common People as aſſertours and maintainors of the Law, Religion and the Kings juſt rights: towards which the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of many have been deſired, and accordingly yeelded; they themſelves having deferted their own Principles acted, in oppoſition to the Law and their owne Oathes and Covenant, as I have made good they are not in theis owne ſence (though for my part I deny that they were ever at firſt in a lawfull ſence ingaged) to take notice of their Ordinances and Commands: But rather to uſe all poſſible law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes for the Reſtoring of his Majeſtie to his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115533:21"/>
juſt Rights, The eſtabliſhed Religion both in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline, to its former purity in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, according to Law, the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> to its ancient genuine freedome, and regular Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and the reſetling of Peace &amp; truth in Church and State.</p>
            <p>And to this effect, becauſe ſome peradventure may apprehend themſelves conſcienciouſly inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the ſolemne League and Covenant to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their aydes in firmly ſetling the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Government; I ſhall for the removing of ſuch obliging apprehenſions (paſſing by the unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of contriving, impoſing, and indeed unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantableneſſe of entring into it at firſt; in which regard I acknowledge it contrary to the Lawes of the Land and authority of Scriptures) give a truely Chriſtian and lawfull conſtruction thereof, as it did at firſt literally, and ſtill doth onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to the takers thereof, who at firſt were not Concatenated Deſigners, and therefore for the better clearing of Mens judgements herein, ſhall firſt propound ſome neceſſary Qualifications and Limitations of Promiſſary Oathes; being bold to affirme, that if any afterwards ſhall obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſiſt in remaining Inſtrumentally Active for this Innovaſion; that I cannot ſee how they can free themſelves from being wilfully guilty of oppoſing Reaſon, Religion and Law, as alſo rending in peeces all holy and obligatory Oathes and Covenants.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115533:21"/>That all Promiſſory lawfull Oaths being religious bonds, muſt be taken in a literall and Gramaticall ſenſe, and all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full endeavours uſed for the performance of each clauſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein, as they plainly appear (not admitting of altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion afterwards, or a contradiction by the mentall Reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Impoſers) at the time of taking thereof to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and underſtanding of him that ſweareth, otherwiſe a man cannot ſweare in Judgement.</p>
            <p>That if any clauſe ſhall be inſerted into any Oath directly oppoſite to the Word of God, or if any part of an Oath can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be obſerved and performed without intrenching upon the breach of Gods Lawes, the one <hi>ipſo facto</hi> is void, for <hi>Rei illici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae nulla obligatio,</hi> and the other ingageth to a<note n="*" place="margin">Impia poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenda promiſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, non perficiend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> repentance on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not to endeavours of performance; for <hi>per juramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum non tenemur niſi ad bonum &amp; legale,</hi> by Oaths men are bound to nothing, but what is lawfull and good, either in reſpect of the end to which Oaths have a reſpect, or meanes conducing to that end; therefore in all ſuch kind of Oaths, their generall conditions ſhould be inſerted, however are neceſſarily implied, <hi>(if I can, if it ſhall pleaſe God, if lawfully I may)</hi> for <hi>nemo tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ad impoſſibile,</hi> and <hi>nil poſſimus quod non de Jure poſſimus;</hi> both poſſible and things lawfull muſt be the ſubſtance of Oaths, otherwiſe we cannot ſweare in righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>That no particular ſentence in a ſecondary Oath deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive unto, or different from any former lawfull ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ought to be kept; therefore any Oath impoſed by the irregular factions of the two Houſes muſt not receive a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, or actions accordingly uſed in oppoſition to the Affirmatively and Negatively Genuine, and commonly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and practiſed ſenſe of the former Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, both lawfull in themſelves, and ſtill according to Law reſting eſtabliſhed, leaſt we adde ſinnes of Omiſſion to ſinnes of Commiſſion; but what is lawfull in any ſecond Oath we muſt performe, what is not, we muſt forbear.</p>
            <p>That in all clauſes in Oaths concerning Reformation, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation or defence of any thing, that thing neceſſarily muſt be extant, muſt have a being, otherwiſe we obliging our ſelves (if we can properly be ſaid to be ingaged to nothing) to nothing,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115533:22"/>
atteſt God as witneſſe thereunto, thereby mocking him, and taking his holy Name in vaine, and in ſo doing erre againſt his third Commandement; therefore the Presbyterian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not being particularly mentioned in the Covenant, nor at the firſt taking thereof, now about foure years and an halfe ſince digeſted in England into any form, much leſſe obedience thereunto commanded, cannot be intended as a fulfilling of the Covenant; but the words <hi>Reforme, preſerve,</hi> and <hi>defend,</hi> muſt have a regard to the Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Government eſtabliſhed: as for that evaſion (that the then takers of the Covenant diſpenſed with reſolutions and actions of preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c. untill the ſame ſhould afterwards be ſetled) it is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unlawfull and vaine; nor can any one by ſo doing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Prophets counſell in Oaths, which muſt be taken in <hi>Righteouſneſſe, Judgement</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed, I proceed to the Oath it ſelf,—only by the way, let me put you in mind of your firſt Oaths of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance and Supremacy, with your Proteſtation, an Epitome of the former in theſe words, <hi>I promiſe, vow and proteſt to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſo far as lawfully I may, his Majeſties Royall Perſon, Honor, and Eſtate; the true Reformed Proteſtant Religion, expreſſed in the Doctrine of the Church of England, &amp;c.</hi> For explanation whereof I referre you to what already hath been ſaid concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Oaths of Allegeance and Supremacy, adviſing every one to conſider ſeriouſly that place in 30. <hi>Numb.</hi> 2. Ver. <hi>If a man vow a Vow unto the Lord, or ſweare an Oath to bind his ſoule with a bond, he ſhall not breake his word, he ſhall do according to all that proceedeth out of his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Solemne League and Covenant.</note>
               <hi>We Noble-men, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Citizens, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes, Miniſters of the Goſpell, and Commons of all ſorts in the Kingdom of England &amp;c. by the providence of God living under one King. Vnder one King,</hi> that according to common ſenſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, muſt imply obedience and ſubjection in us unto him as a King enabled with power to governe, and that obedience muſt preſuppoſe a rule of reaſon, and law, (now what that Law is, I have already handled) to ſquare our actions of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience by.</p>
            <p>O that the people of England, &amp;c. would in in this reſpect
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115533:22"/>
obey the Precept of Chriſt,—<hi>Give unto Caeſar what belongs unto Caeſar;</hi> His Majeſtie never expected more then what the Law manifeſteth to be juſtly his,<note place="margin">Witneſſe all his Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> why then ſhould we give him leſſe? Nay, endeavour to deprive him altogether of what we have neither reaſon, nor juſt power to attempt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And being of one reformed Religion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note>—This muſt neceſſarily intend our Religion eſtabliſhed, a Religion that is, not that ſhall be, which Religion commandeth obedience to all His Majeſties lawfull commands, denieth the Subjects Liberty to take up armes againſt their lawfull Soveraigne, acknowledgeth him to be Supreme in <hi>all cauſes, and over all perſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide homilies, &amp; 37. Artic. Church Engl.</note> 
               <hi>as well Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall as Civill, &amp;c.</hi> that to him properly and wholly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth the government of all Eſtates of this Realme, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without and againſt his conſent, no different Government can be introduced.<note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Having before our eyes the glory of God.</hi>—God is never more glorified then when we expreſſe a willing obedience to his commands two whereof emphatically enjoyne obedience to Superiors, and forbid wrong and prejudice to be offered by any to any one whomſoever.—</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Honour thy Father and Mother,</hi> that is, all thoſe that have authority over us, as all Expoſitors upon good grounds render the meaning of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet thy Neighbours houſe, &amp;c. nor any thing that is his;</hi>—that is, thou ſhalt not wiſh thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours hinderance in any thing, much leſſe deprive him of the leaſt thing properly belonging unto him,<note place="margin">Vide the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> or you ſhall not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any wrong to any man whomſoever, whereby he may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer damage in perſon, eſtate, reputation, or otherwiſe; for the word <hi>neighbour,</hi> muſt be taken in a more extenſive ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Commandement, then we commonly uſe it. O that every man with one eye fixed upon theſe two Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments would with the other view what by the Law is juſtly due to his Majeſtie, and Poſterity, and then conſider, &amp;c. Beſides theſe you have the Prophets and Apopoſtles,<note place="margin">Pro. 27.29.30.</note> ſpeaking the ſame truth as Ambaſſadours from heaven; <hi>Solomon</hi> adviſeth us not to with-hold the goods from the owners thereof, though
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115533:23"/>
there be power in thy hand to do it,<note place="margin">Prov. 3.27, 29, 30.</note> nor to intend hurt againſt our neighbour, ſeeing he doth dwell by us without<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Feare,</hi> that is, putteth truſt in us. Pro. 24.21. Eccleſ. 8.3, 4. Vide margent in the Bible. Covenant.</note> feare, not to ſtrive with a man cauſleſſe, ſeeing he hath done no harme, <hi>My ſonne fear the Lord and the King, and meddle not with thoſe that are given to change,</hi> ſaith the ſame wiſeman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Take heed to the mouth of the King, and to the Word of the Oath of God,</hi> ſaith the Preacher,— that is, obey the King, and keep the Oath that thou had made for the ſame cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The advancement of the Kingdome of our Lord and Savior Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Kingdome is never more advanced then when we obey his Precepts, and imitate his practice.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.16.</note>Now his Precepts will appear in part, if we conſider that in his Sermon upon the Mount, after he had pronounced bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe to the poore in ſpirit, to thoſe that mourne, to the meeke, to thoſe which hunger and thirſt for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to the pure in heart, to peace-makers, to thoſe which ſuffer for righteouſneſſe ſake, to thoſe that are falſly revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and perſecuted; he addeth this Exhortation to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,— <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine,</hi> that is, let theſe things for which men ſhall be bleſſed, practically appeare in your lives and converſations, that ſo they may <hi>ſee your good workes,</hi> that is, others by your example of holineſſe may be brought home to the fold of Chriſt, and <hi>glorifie his Father which is in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for his practiſe you may read it in reſpect of his pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tribute, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21. as alſo how that being brought before Rulers whom (though cauſeleſly reviling of him) hee reviled not againe, being led as a ſheep to the ſlaughter, and obedient unto death, that thereby hee might be a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne for our imitation, to which purpoſe he invites us, <hi>Follow me for I am lowly and meeke, &amp;c.</hi> and in our imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we muſt follow him, in obeying his Meſſengers the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles counſells, for they are ſent from him, and what their counſell was, you may peruſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>ſubmit your ſelves unto the higher Powers, &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14, 17. <hi>be obedient to every Ordinance of man, for the Lords ſake, whether unto the King as ſupreme, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115533:23"/>Now what is this but to advance the Kingdome of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The honour and happineſſe of the King,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Covenant.</note> honour him as a King of England by a cheerfull obedience unto his Lawes, in which conſiſts his greateſt happineſſe: ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him by your aſſiſtance as Subjects, ſupporting and ſuſtaining him by your ſupplies according to his impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant occaſions calling for the ſame: For, as Chriſt advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Apoſtles to expreſſe their affections by keeping of his Commandements, <hi>if you love me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>keep my Commandements,</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, if you love me you will keep my Commandements, and if you doe keep my Commandements, you then evidence that you love me; ſo in this reſpect <hi>obedience</hi> to and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of His Majeſtie are but expreſſions of honour, if you honour the King you will obey and aſſiſt him, if you obey and aſſiſt him, you make it appeare to the world that you do really honour him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Royall Poſterity,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Covenant.</note> what Honour and Rights were juſtly due to the Father, render to his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, deprive not them of any part of their inheritance, their regall honour and power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The publike liberty, ſafety and peace of the Kingdome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That muſt needs imply the<note n="*" place="margin">Magna Charta.</note> Law; for, by that we are diſtinguiſhed from ſlaves; and in that we have ſecurity and ſafety with peace, the fruit of the obſervation of the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein every ones private condition is included.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That is, Prince as well as people: O Lord bleſſe the Kings Majeſty and royall Poſterity, reſtore our Lawes to their vigor, and this poore Kingdome to a laſting peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calling to mind the conſpiracies and practices of the enemies of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note> 
               <hi>againſt the true Religion and profeſſors thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, againſt the doctrinall part of our Religion,<note place="margin">Vide the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of an oath behind.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the 39. Articles of the Church of England: for common reaſon and your Proteſtation affirmeth it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily meant of our Religion eſtabliſhed, and againſt the maintainers, thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115533:24"/>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
               <hi>Calling to mind the treacherous and bloody plots againſt the Law of the Kingdome,</hi>— that is, plots by ſuch waies and meanes, as the deplorable eſtate of Ireland long ſince was a ſad witneſſe of, whoſe rebellious and trayterors courſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt His Majeſties Royall Perſon, Crowne of England and Ireland, ſufficiently then ſpake their intentions to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert both Religion and Law.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
               <hi>We have now at laſt for preſervation of our ſelves and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion from utter ruine and deſtruction</hi>— That againe, I ſay, according to reaſon, muſt have a reſpect to a Religion and Law that is eſtabliſhed; for it is improper and abſurd to ſay, much more vaine to ſweare, that I will preſerve that from ruine and deſtruction which is not in being, ruine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſing ſomthing that is to be deſtroyed; and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſomthing that otherwiſe will be ruined.</p>
            <p>Thus you have the ground of this Covenant, (without mentall reſervation and equivocation, which if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers had any, as ſince it appears they had, <hi>non ad vos per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet,</hi> it ſavoureth too much of the Jeſuite, <hi>ipſi viderint,</hi> let them look to it, it concerneth not you to whom I write) according to the literall and Gramaticall ſenſe and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Rules of Religion, Reaſon and Law explained; I proceed to the Covenant it ſelfe, wherein I ſhall obſerve the ſame religious, rationall and lawfull method.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">i Art. Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note>
               <hi>That we ſhall ſincerely, really and conſtantly (through the grace of God) endeavour in our ſeverall places and callings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, according to the ſtation wherein God hath placed us, the King in his regall Power, Magiſtrates as deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatives from him in their places, Miniſters in theirs, private ſubordinate perſons according to their ſeverall degrees in theirs, none exceeding the rules proper to their peculiar Vocation; where by the way take notice, that although Superiours may and often do at one and the ſelf-ſame time performe both their owne duties and alſo actions proper to Inferiours, yet it is unlawfull for Inferiours to take upon them without lawfull Commiſſion the duty of Superiours; Lay private men muſt not in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ermeddle with what concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115533:24"/>
the proper duty of a Miniſter, nor muſt Divines wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully intrench upon the bounds of the Civill Magiſtrates, nor they upon the Royall Fuction of the King; for this were to authorize confuſion, whereas God is the God of Order.<note place="margin">Covenant:</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Endeavour</hi> (<note n="*" place="margin">That clauſe muſt be impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed though not inſerted. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it is alſo confeſſed as needfull in the exhortation for taking the Covenant, Ordered by the Houſe of Commons, <hi>Die Veneris</hi> Feb. 1643. Covenant.</note> 
               <hi>ſo far as lawfully I may) the preſervation of the Reformed Religion in the Church of Scotland in Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, if their Reformed Religion be not contrary to the Word of God: this I adde, becauſe few in England know what it is in its Doctrinall part, but by an implicite faith; and I adde it the rather, becauſe the practice of the prevailing party there ſince theſe ſtormes firſt begun, ſo contrary to profeſſions, may occaſion ſuſpition of their doctrines ſincere truth, witneſſe their Declarations, and therein Proteſtations to maintaine the Kings Rights, &amp;c. contradicted by aſſiſting endeavours to deprive him of his Rights.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In worſhip, diſcipline and government.</hi> That is, that Government which was eſtabliſhed, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained at the compiling of the Covenant, grant it the Presbyterian, by the lawfull and ſupreme pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of that Kingdome, untill that government ſhall be altered by virtue of the ſelf-ſame power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Againſt our common enemies.</hi> That is,<note place="margin">Covenant.</note> all who by unlawfull meanes, contrary to the Word of God, the Lawes and cuſtomes of that Nation, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his Royall Majeſty, ſhall indeavour an infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced alteration thereof. And here by the way, as well for vindication of my ſelf and many others in England, as alſo ſeeing they eſteem the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Government there ſo rich a purchaſed jewell, for their future ſecurity; I ſhall add thus much, that ſince they enjoyed that government ſo confirmed as they have by the Royall aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, we never would have
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115533:25"/>
diſturbed them in their deſired poſſeſſion of their Church-government; as they have viſited (for I love mildneſſe in expreſſions in what concerneth my Countries intereſt) us by oaths and armes for an extirpation of Epiſcopacy, and for the future ſhall never intermeddle contrary to Reaſon, Religion or Law.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
               <hi>The reformation of religion in the Kingdome of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government. according to the Word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the doctrine of the Church of England expreſſed in the<note n="*" place="margin">The doctrine of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church in Ireland a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to them.</note> 39. Articles, being grounded on a ſure foundation, the holy Scriptures (which are onely able to make us wiſe unto ſalvation) hath even to this very day, by the aſſiſtance, protection and efficaciouſly working of Gods Spirit in the hearts of many glorious pillars of our Church (reverend Biſhops and other pious and learned Divines) ſtood like a rock unſhaken, their tongues preaching, their pens maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, their bloods confirming the irreſiſtable prevailing truth thereof, againſt Turke, Jew, Jeſuite, and all other he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall and ſchiſmaticall opponents whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Thus much I am confident all neighbouring Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches will condeſcend unto: therefore I ſhall proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
               <hi>In Doctrine and Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, all erroneous tenents and practices (whether Papiſticall, Schiſmaticall, or others) of thoſe <hi>qui ambulant poſt ſpiritum ſuum,</hi> againſt whom the Prophet denounceth a woe,<note place="margin">Ezek. 13.3.</note> who being departed from the<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1.</note> faith which they once profeſſed, are guided by the ſpirit of error, leading ſilly women, and unſtable mindes captive, by the whiſtling of every breath of their windy doctrine, being clad in ſheeps cloathing,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.15.</note> but inwardly ravenous Wolves: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of which nature, too too many offer them- themſelves in theſe unhappy times; wherein almoſt all
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115533:25"/>
things are countenanced, or at leaſt connived at as lawful, but lawful things; therefore let us pray, That the God of Peace and Truth would bring into the way of Truth and Peace all ſuch as have erred and been deceived, by ſeditious Schiſmatical guids, and erronious directions, and proſper thou, oh Lord, all their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours tending to ſuch a Reformation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diſcipline, Government according to the Word of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note> 
               <hi>and the beſt Reformed Churches.</hi> —</p>
            <p>Now the queſtion will be, which cometh neareſt to the Word of God.</p>
            <p>That Epiſcopacy claimeth the neareſt alliance, truly entituling it ſelf to be of Apoſtolical Inſtitution, is a truth that hath been made good in all ages.</p>
            <p>That for 1500 years continuance of Chriſtianity, there is no example of the Church Governed otherwiſe: An Argument ſufficient to ſuſpect Novelties in oppoſition unto it.</p>
            <p>That it hath been approved of by moſt of the Proteſtant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines beyond the Seas,<note place="margin">Vide Eccleſiaſt Hiſtori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (who are rather induced by neceſſity to the practiſe of Presbytery, there wanting means to maintain, or abilities lawfully to compaſs Epiſcopal Government, them wills and deſires to enjoy the ſame: A ſtrong Argument, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading that our Church is the beſt Reformed:) is alſo an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent truth.</p>
            <p>That in all diſputes, eſpecially this latter,<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Hall</hi> againſt 1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11. SMECTYMNVVS Since the War</note> of the reverend and learned Remonſtrancer, againſt that odd Combination of * Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Epiſcopacy hath ſtood the field, triumphing in Reaſon and Religion, which have only perſwaded my judgment to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination thereunto, and an approbation thereof; and I preſume any one, not obſtinately prejudicate in their judgments, will ſoon be ſatisfied thereof, and agree with me herein; by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of that learned Biſhops writings, or by any, whoſe learning and judgments are able to inform them therein.</p>
            <p>But to write truth, whether Epiſcopacy or Presbytery come neareſt to the Word of God, never was, nor at preſent is, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute between His Majeſty and the two Houſes; but <hi>quis reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabit?</hi> Where the ſupream power, in Cauſes Eccleſiaſticall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115533:26"/>
and Civil ſhall practically remain for the future, either in Prince or people: Nor indeed was it the end, that theſe Covenant-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers did aim at. Witneſs their ſecond Article, wherein before tryal and examination (whereby truth or falſhood is made evident,) they, contrary to reaſon, paſs ſentence of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon it; therein poſitively ſwearing, without reſpect of perſons, (a ſtrange expreſſion, whereas the King is the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wheel of a new Law) to extirpate the Government it ſelf, that indeed being a Marble pillar, which firſt muſt be removed by them, before they can introduce their bloody-colour'd poſt of Presbytery; endeavouring in that Article to ingage the common peoples Conſciences, (though I ſhall by and by make good, that no mans Conſcience is thereby ingaged) to aſſiſt them, I mean the Plotters, to attain that which they had a pre-reſolution to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, <hi>ſi non Precibus tunc vi, armiſque:</hi> —Since that plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing as I have already ſhewed.</p>
            <p>However that my deceived Countrymen may ſee how they have been abuſed into a belief of enjoying I know not how much happineſs under the term of Reformation in Church, now generally re-baptized Presbytery; I ſhall preſent to your veiw a ſhort Paralel, collected out of the writings of a pious, learned and conſcientious Divine, of theſe two Governments, Epiſcopal and Presbyterian.<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Fearne</hi>
               </note> For, as for that illegitimate thing, that new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born brat Independency, it hath ſuch variety of ſhapes, and each of them alſo ſo monſtrous, that I ſhall not need to meddle with it at all, being Confident that it will ſoon be hiſſed out of the Kingdom by a Univerſal Conſent, or like <hi>Jonah</hi>'s gourd vaniſh away, unthought of, in a moment. And here I cannot but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert my admiration, to perceive ſo many men ſtill ſo firmly in their affections and Judgments, adhering to the preſent conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive determinations of that changeable-coloured thing, nay, that word <hi>Parliament;</hi> when as it is that which hath ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed even theſe firſt affecting perſons, the City of <hi>London</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, their miſ-lead ſupporters: Witneſs in particular, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent continuing impriſonment of the Lord Mayor, and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and that ſtrange and uncivil expulſion out of the Leiutenan, cy of the Tower, that deſerving Gentleman Col. <hi>Francis Weſt</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115533:26"/>
without the leaſt pretended cauſe, even in the very middeſt of his expreſſed courteſies, and feaſting favours cofenr'd upon their great Don, and his followers; although he formerly was choſen by the general Vote, nay, acclamation of the whole City, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of by themſelves, and indeed beloved by all; Only to make way for that unfl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dg'd Titmouſe of Manhood and Wit; that Imp of Independency <hi>Tichbourn,</hi> fitter, by far, mimically, again in his Fathers Chamber, to act a wanton girles part in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, then to have ſo great a part of truſt and commanding power, as he now hath conferred upon him. Oh Lord open the eyes of poor deceived <hi>England,</hi> eſpecially the City of <hi>London,</hi> and ſuffer them no longer to walk in darkneſs, and in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a ſenceleſs ſtupidity, thus like blind men, groping for the path of peace and truth, even at noon day.</p>
            <p>But I proceed to the Paralel of theſe Eccleſiaſtical Governments. And in the firſt place, take their defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in general.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Epiſcopacy, in it ſelf conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is a prelacy or ſuperiority of one above all the Presbyters, within ſuch a precinct or dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, which one is appointed to have care of all the Churches within that compaſs, and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with Power and Authority for Ordination and Juriſdiction (that Authority not being Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary, but bounded by Laws,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115533:27"/>
and adminiſtred or exerciſed with advice and aſſiſtance of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in choyce Presbyters;) to the intent, that all Churches or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations under him may be provided of able Paſtors, and that both theſe inferior Paſtors and people may perform the duties required of them.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115533:26"/>Preſsbytery is ſuch a form of Church-Government,<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Fearn</hi> in his book of Epiſcopacy &amp; Presbytery conſidered.</note> as is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred by preaching, and Lay Elders joyntly, with equal voice and power in the ſeveral Judicatories of their Parochial Seſſions, of their Claſſical or greater Conſiſtories, of their P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ovincial Synods,<note place="margin">Page 3</note> and Nation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Aſſemblies.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115533:27"/>Now by this, if I miſtake not, you may perceive that they both agree in <hi>ipſo regimine Eccleſiaſtico,</hi> —in the Government it ſelf, conſidered as it referreth to the Church, that is, all Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers therein that are to be governed, though not in the manner, number or qualification of the perſons governing; both parties confeſſing, that the power of Ordination, and of Judicature, (ſo far forth as the keys left by Chriſt in his Church do extend) is of Divine Inſtitution, and that this power muſt be exceciſed or adminiſtred in his Church by ſome; ſo that, I ſay, the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is, whether the exerciſe or miniſtration of that power be reſtrained to certain choice men, or indifferently left to all Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and their aſſiſting Lay Elders: — For none will accuſe themſelves guilty of ſo much ignorance and folly, as to affirm, that the decent Ceremonies, and innocent Veſtm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s of the Church, as Croſs in Baptiſm, Surpleſs, Cope &amp;, the like, were pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed &amp; impoſed, as eſſential, and inſeparably neceſſary adjuncts to the Government it ſelf: All which, rather then contention for them, ſhould have extended to blood, might, nay would have been, by the condeſcention of His Majeſty, quietly layd aſide, needing not the peremptorineſs of the ſword to ſilence them.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I. Under epiſcopal there is in every Pariſh a preaching Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, with Churchwardens; and in ſome Deacons or Curates, by theſe offenders are noted and admoniſhed, and the offences preſented to the Eccleſiaſtical Courts or Confiſtories, where they may be heard and cenſured
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115533:27"/>
the Miniſter having power in ſome caſes of notorious ſcandal, to reſtrain from the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, untill the offence may be heard and judged in the Court and the party ſo offending, by the cenſure of the Church brought to give publike ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115533:27"/>Under the Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment there is in every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh a Miniſter, with a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent number of Lay Elders and Deacons; according to the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Pariſh: Theſe make the Parochial Seſſion, and have power to cenſure ſcandalous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, contentious perſons, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115533:27"/>
the like, to enjoyn publike pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and impoſe upon the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, before he be received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, a fine to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed on pious uſes.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>II. Under Epiſcopal, in every dioceſs, there are ſeveral diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the leſſer and the greater, theſe being called Deanries, there is Arch-Deconries, in thoſe the Arch-Presbyters, in theſe the Arch-Deacons have power to call the Parochial Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters together to enquire of doctrine and manners, and ſee to the redreſſing of ſmaller abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. In the Mother City is the Biſhop reſiding with his Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, having the power of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of judging and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of all matter of doctrine or ſcandal, reſerevd to his hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by his Arch-Deacons, and of rejudging what was judged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs by them: This he doth, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Conſiſtory, which he holdeth in his City, aſſiſted by his Presbyters; or in his Vſitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, going through his dioceſs, and cauſing his Clergy perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to appear, or in his dioceſan Synod, which is made up of the City Presbyters, <hi>Dean</hi> and <hi>Chapter,</hi> the Arch-Deacons, and other choice Presbyters under the preſidency of the Biſhop.</cell>
                     <cell>Under the Presbyterian in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry County, there are alſo ſeveral diviſions or Claſſes, containing ſuch a number of Parochiall Miniſters, who have their ſet meetings for conference; and in the City, or more eminent Town, is the great Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Conſiſtory, commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Presbytery, made up of all the Parochiall Miniſters within its precincts; and of Lay Elders, from each Pariſh one; in this is the power of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of cenſuring crimes of the higher ſtrain, with the greater Excommunication of hearing appeals from the Parochial Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and rejudging what was there judged amiſs.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115533:28"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>III. Under Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are held Provincial Synods, conſiſting of all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Deans, Arch-Deacons, and of certain choice Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from every dioceſs within the Province; theſe have power to order all matters concerning the whole Province, to hear ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals from every Dioceſs, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judg what is done amiſs, that could not be well determined in a Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ceſan Synod.</cell>
                     <cell>Under the Presbyterian alſo are held Provincial Synods, made up of Commiſſioners, that is, certain preaching, and Lay Elders from every Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Presbytery, or Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Conſiſtory, within the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince: Theſe judg and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine matters pertaining to the whole Province: Alſo, all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult caſes, that could not well be determined within the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, they receive appeals al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo from the Presbyters, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine what was there thought to be done amiſs.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>IIII. Under Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are alſo held National Councels, conſiſting of the like Members as do the Provincial, theſe are of greateſt au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hority: they examine and judg any thing done amiſs any in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince: they conſider and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine matters of Doctrine and Diſcipline inorder to the whole Nationall Church.</cell>
                     <cell>Under the Presbyterian, likewiſe, are held National Aſſemblies, conſiſting of Commiſſioners from all the Presbyteries in the Kingdom, each of them ſending two preaching, and one Lay Elder; alſo from every Burrough one, and he a Lay man; and from every Univerſity one, and for the moſt part a Ley man too: In theſe is the ſupream and finall determination of all complaints and controverſies, and unto the decrees that iſſue thence, all muſt obey under pain of Excommunication.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe premiſes impartially conſidered, which of theſe two Governments have the more effectual means to procure the end of Church Government, the preſervation of truth and peace, the ſuppreſſion of Hereſie and Schiſm, let any rational unbyaſs'd-minded man judg; For my part, I ingenuouſly confeſs that it is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115533:28"/>
contrary to common reaſon, in my apprehenſion, that Lay-men, from whoſe education no knowledg extraordinary beyond their trades and ſuch like affairs can be expected, (although it is true that many are furniſhed with knowing parts, yet as true that the moſt in a Nation are altogether defective therein) can be as fit inſtruments for ſuch kind of imployments as grave and learned Divines, whoſe only buſineſs it is to tread the path of all arts both humane and divine; ſo that if this continue in <hi>England,</hi> what I once read alledged againſt the Papal Conſiſtory, that they did <hi>potius numerare ſuffragia quam argumenta pondirare;</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber rather their Votes, then weigh the ſolidity of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments; will, I fear, be our deſerved cenſure.</p>
            <q>
               <l>From which juſtly meriting accuſation</l>
               <l>Good Lord deliver this Nation.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Again conſider further, Biſhops aſſume not the exerciſe of any power within any Princes Dominions, or uſe it over his ſubjects but by permiſſion and authority from him, and that according to juſt Laws and Rules made by ſoveraign Authority for the manner of external Miniſtration thereof, ſo that when the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal power cometh to the holding of Courts and calling Aſſemblies, it wholy depends on the ſoveraign power;<note place="margin">25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.19.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whoſe Aſſent, ſignified by his writ, they cannot aſſemble for the making of Canons and Conſtitutions, nor publiſh and put in u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e any of them being made.</p>
            <p>Now Presbyterians take upon them to ſet up their Diſcipline in a Kingdom (therein indeed ſhaking hands with Jeſuited Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,) maugre all oppoſition; It is true for external peace ſake they hold it fit to crave leave firſt and beg the aſſiſtance of the Civil Power, but if denyed, will proceed without it, aſſembling together and making their own Laws without regulations from the Civil Power, for the manner and form of exerciſing their Diſcipline, allowing only the Prince, <hi>Potestatem Cumulativam</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115533:29"/>
(as they ſpeak) a power to add more ſtrength and vigour, not <hi>Privativam,</hi> to interpoſe or hinder their aſſemblies or decrees. And in this reſpect it were to be wiſhed that <hi>England</hi> had never proved exemplary, as now in theſe latter times it doth by ſuch kind of proceedings; The fountain from whence hath iſſued too ny bloody ſtreams.</p>
            <p>And here it will not be amiſs to preſent the Reader with the grounds and reaſons enforcing his Majeſty with his loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects aſſiſtance to defenſive Arms, and in that a Declaration of my own in particular and many thouſand Engliſh Proteſtant Judgments more, whoſe pens, tongues and hands only endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored a reſtoration of his Royal Majeſty to his juſt regal honor and authority.</p>
            <p>Themſelves and their fellow-ſubjects unto their due liberties both Parliamentary and private.</p>
            <p>The preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion in the Doctrine and Profeſſion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt all Papiſts and Sectaries.</p>
            <p>The maintenance of the Government of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as it ſtandeth ſtill by Law eſtabliſhed until the Law of the Land ſhall make alteration thereof; not ſo peremptorily maintaining the continuance of Epiſcopal Government, as to enforce the remaining of its general practice in <hi>England,</hi> by force of Arms in oppoſition and againſt his Majeſties (ſuppoſe that the King could or would diſpence with his Coronation Oath) will and conſent to that purpoſe cheerfully and voluntarily ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified; (not by the preſſing violence of almoſt unavoydable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity or tyrannizing power of the prevailing Sword) but freely confirmed and declared by Act of Parliament, although perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture they may mourn the alteration and abrogation of ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and apoſtolical a Government.</p>
            <p>But becauſe my Judgment pleadeth for <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and it hath been an argument much urged againſt the Biſhops, and in them the Government it ſelf defamed — That</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115533:29"/>That formerly they ſilenced ſeverall godly Miniſters, prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting them and others the exerciſe of holy duties; becauſe they did only exerciſe duties that were holy; I ſhal write my thoughts freely herein; For, far be it from me to ſpeak againſt, or any to forbid the Exerciſe of holy duties, as hearing, praying, reading, living ſtrictly, <hi>Endeavouring to have a Conſcience void of offence towards God, and towards Men:</hi> No, no, the practice of them in ſincerity is the high way to Heaven, for <hi>without holineſſe none ſhall ſee God;</hi> but in the mean time, take heed what you hear, beware of ſwallowing poyſon wrapped up in Leaves of gold; take heed of theſe who have a <hi>forme of Godlineſſe,</hi> a forme in Practice onely; that <hi>under pretence of long Prayers</hi> and outſide piety, <hi>devour Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows houſes,</hi> that deny the truth of the word of God, the holy Scriptures; by their <hi>falſe Doctrines</hi> ſeducing many into <hi>erronious Opinions,</hi> the parents of worſe ſucceeding actions.</p>
            <p>For my part, if any did ſo forbid <hi>performance of holy duties,</hi> as I am altogether ignorant of any ſuch; nor can eaſily be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to believe it, howſoever were I aſſured of its truth, I would not <hi>minima defendere peccata,</hi> plead an excuſe for them.</p>
            <p>But if then they did (as I believe they did) onely by <hi>ſuſpenſions</hi> endeavour to prevent the ſowing of the ſeeds of <hi>ſedition, ſchiſme</hi> and <hi>hereſie,</hi> or the growth thereof to any ſtrength, either in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick or in private, (as it was there) and is the duty of all <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Governours,</hi> they did no more then what the law of God and the land gave them a warrant for; therefore let every one as well take heed of calling <hi>good, evill;</hi> as tearming <hi>evill</hi> to be <hi>good:</hi> for in all probability, had ſuch preventing-remedies as theſe been timely applied, when <hi>ſedition, ſchiſme</hi> and <hi>hereſie</hi> firſt opened their black mouths, we never had arrived at this high degree (as at this preſent we are) of variety of Errours and pernicious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Opinions— <hi>O Lord have mercy upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But grant that ſome of them ſtretched the <hi>exerciſe of power</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond its lawfull bounds, and in that reſpect were guilty, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving puniſhment.</p>
            <p>What, is the fault of <hi>one</hi> or more <hi>Biſhops</hi> to the Government it ſelf? could not the <hi>errours of particular perſons</hi> be <hi>reformed,</hi> or <hi>puniſhed</hi> but by an <hi>extirpation</hi> of the whole Government? <hi>durus eſt hic ſermo,</hi> it is hard indeed, if God for the ſin of two, <hi>Adam</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115533:30"/>
and <hi>Eve,</hi> nay of many thouſands more, ſhould have therefore denied <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>reconciliation to all mankind.</hi> How everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unhappy would the reſidue of the world have been! <hi>Deliver us good God from the cruell dealings of men, and if affliction muſt be our portion, let us fall into thy hands, O Lord, for thy mercy endureth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the remaining clauſes in the firſt Article, <hi>viz. Of bringing the Churches of God in the three Kingdoms to the neareſt uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c.</hi> theſe things conſidered:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
               <hi>That the Diſcipline of the Church of God is most Conſonant to the word of God, approved of, and deſired by forraigne Divines,</hi> and therefore the beſt reformed; not intrenching with the <hi>Papiſts</hi> upon the <hi>Civill power,</hi> nor with them, denying <hi>the Kings ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> agreeing beſt with Monarchy, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Law of the Land. Other Churches therefore (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of reaſon and religion) within His Majeſties Dominions, ſhould rather conform to ours, then the uniformity of <hi>ours</hi> in <hi>Religion, Government,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> admit a <hi>change,</hi> or be transformed into any other form: To this purpoſe, <hi>O Lord, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire the univerſal Church with the ſpirit of truth, unity, and concord, and grant that all that do Confeſſe thy holy name may live in peace and godly love one with another. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Covenant.</hi> This limitation is approved by the Parliament, as behind, <hi>fol.</hi> 53.</note>
               <hi>That we ſhall in like manner;</hi> that is, in a lawfull manner ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word of God, <hi>endevour the extirpation of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> — that is, their tenents of <hi>tranſubſtantiation, worſhipping of Images, praying to Saints, Preaching good works as meritorious to everlaſting life and ſalvation, that Kings for diverſe reſpects may be Depoſed by the people, that then Subjects Oaths of Alleagiance may be diſpenſed with,</hi>
               <note place="margin">King <hi>James Apol.</hi> Oath Alleg.</note> 
               <hi>with their deniall of the Kings Supremacy in all Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as well Eccleſiaſticall and Civill,</hi> and the like; Endeavour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of theſe by execution of good Laws already eſtabliſhed againſt their Errours and Profeſſours thereof, by that meanes preventing their further growth, hindring their ſeducing of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and unwary people, and in caſe of Conſpiracy and Treaſon againſt the Kings Majeſty, His Queen, or Royall off-ſpring, the diſturbance of the Peace of Church and State, by complaining of their attempts and deeds to the Magiſtrate, leaving them to the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115533:30"/>
juſtice of the Law: and laſtly, by recovering them by ſtrength of holy arguments (as with ſtrong phiſick) from that infection of their <hi>judgment</hi> and <hi>conſciences,</hi> and their ſoul-poyſoning <hi>hereſies,</hi> praying continually in the fervency of the ſpirit for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed to the next words (<hi>Extirpation of Church-Government by Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c.) I muſt deſire the Reader to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect back upon what I have already written concerning the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitations of an Oath,</hi> briefly thus, <hi>That no unlawfull Oath bindeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide fol. <hi>46.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nor muſt unlawfull means be uſed for the compaſſing for effecting any thing in it ſelf lawfull, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Extirpation of Government by Arch-biſhops, Biſhops,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note> 
               <hi>their Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, &amp;c.</hi> That is, by uſing all lawfull means warrantable by the law of God and the Kingdome, to that end, as petitioning the ſupream Magiſtrate the <hi>King,</hi> or any other way if any other way can be imagined, not I ſay, intrenching upon the law of God.</p>
            <p>For, were an abolition hereof abſolutely neceſſary, conducing to the generall peace of the Kingdom, as it is upon good grounds, believed, rather altogether diſtructive thereunto; will you buy a temporall peace upon ſuch unequal termes, as to hazard your ſoul eternally (unleſſe the mercy of God interpoſe) by wilfull perjury in the purchaſe, and gain an eating curſe to your Poſterity by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge? Beſides, it is againſt the Principles of all Governments, the Law of God, and the Land, to enforce an alteration by bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy force, as I have already ſhewed.</p>
            <p>Nay, you doe not onely hereby make your ſelves guilty of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, treaſon, bloud</hi> and <hi>ſacriledge,</hi> but you endeavour to <hi>compell His Majeſty to the breach of His Oath taken at His Coronation,</hi> wherein <hi>He ſwore to Defend the Biſhops, their priviledges, and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches under their government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, were the <hi>Preſbyterian government</hi> abſolutely good, &amp; ſo out of neceſſity the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> muſt be removed, as it is not, yet a bloudy eradication is <hi>proculdubio,</hi> unlawfull, for <hi>we muſt not do evill, that good may come thereof;</hi> we muſt not like mad Mariners <hi>deſperately</hi> ſteer our courſe amongſt Rocks, hoping to arrive at a rich freight, leſt we ſhipwrack our ſelves here, and loſe the end of our voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, our hopes hereafter; therefore let all men, take heed of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115533:31"/>
a neceſſity of keeping this one Article of extirpation, becauſe they have ſo Covenanted; unleſſe they will make good alſo a neceſſity of breaking all Gods Commandements; which is an high degree of Blaſphemy to maintain, for that is, <hi>impia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſio quae ſine ſcelere impleri non poteſt, non<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> obligat;</hi> no Law ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth in oppoſition to the Gods Law; if it doth binde, it is to a repentance only; Therefore Recollect your thoughts now, for your owne Experience cannot but acquainte you, that a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent deprivation of the Kings Regall power was at firſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers deſigne; and now plainly appeareth to be the Reſult of the Warre on their part; and reflect upon the almoſt ſix years means made uſe of; or rather ſinnes committed to effect the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment thereof; as Envy, Hatred, Malice, Hypocriſie, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick pretences of Reformation, private intentions of Eradication, and Deformation, revilings of His Majeſties Royall Perſon and Government, Scandalizing of the Engliſh Nationall Church, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Lying, contempt of Superiors, forceing of mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, Diſloyalty, Perjury, Theft, Bloodſhedding, nay, all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Sinnes, with renewing of old Hereſies, and raiſing of all manner of Schiſmes. Now if you love your ſelves and your ſoules, and would not contract the guilt of all theſe ſinnes upon your owne heads; and as it were ſet your Seal of confirmation and approbation to the Sinnes of others; thus <hi>heaping up wrath againſt the day of wrath,</hi> be perſwaded to deſert theſe Plotters, and their Deſignes perſiſt not; (contrary to Reaſon and Religion) in a rigid and ſinfull keeping of that extirpating Article. Now ſeeing the day-ſtar appeareth, and every one (who formerly were wraped up in the night of miſtakes and miſapprehenſions, or blinded with the ſilken veile of a good Opinion of the Contrivers, (becauſe outwardly they appeared in Angelicall habits) may without ſpectacles read that their pretences were only to uſher in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; therefore the plea of ignorance and good meaning as formerly, can no longer be uſed, but be perſwaded to come out from among theſe progreſſive ROOTERS, leſt continuing with them in Sinne; you alſo with them partake of puniſhment. For God is juſt, as well as mercifull.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
               <hi>Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſme, and Profaneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> For the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of this ſecond Article having already written ſomething
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115533:31"/>
(which alſo may aptly be applyed to theſe) when I handled the word <hi>Popery,</hi> I ſhall only turne it into a Prayer; yet becauſe Schiſme is joyned with the reſt; if it were a time in theſe ſad times, to jeſt, I ſhould make it good, Rationally that your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving Presbyterians have in that, Sworn againſt their owne Practice; for although the Proteſtant Church, like the <hi>Spouſe</hi> in the <hi>Canticles</hi> is <hi>black;</hi> that is, not appearing <hi>genuina gloria,</hi> by reaſon of ſtormy weather; yet ſtill ſhe is <hi>Comly;</hi> ſtill in her doctrine and diſcipline unaltered, remaining firme upon its old eſtabliſhed foundation, notwithſtanding the violent Endeavours of their changing times; nor was their Presbyterian Government then extant, and as yet but an infant, for want of the Royall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, being neither able to ſtand, goe, or ſpeak; they themſelves alſo very well knew, what the word <hi>Schiſme</hi> in an Eccleſiaſticall ſenſe meaneth; how that <hi>ille Schiſmaticus qui a ritu Eccleſiae petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanter, &amp; ambitionis ſtudio diſcedit;</hi> that Separateth himſelfe upon a proud Phariſaicall conceit of holineſſe from the Communion of the Church, in the performance of Religious acts. But I paſſe that by, Praying that God, the ſearcher of all hearts, would be pleaſed to root out of all our hearts and mindes the deſtroying blindneſſe of Superſtition, the ſpreading Leproſie of Hereſie, the peace-Eating Gangren of Schiſme, the tainting Corrupt humours of Profaneſſe, and all other things diſpleaſing unto him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to His word, that we enjoy a bleſſed harmonious conſent in Truth and Godlineſſe, expreſſing the power thereof in our lives and converſations, and that the Lord may be One, and his name One in theſe three Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſhall with the ſame ſincerity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3</hi> Article. Covenant.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Endeavour to preſerve the Rights and Priviledges of Parliament:</hi> Theſe are — freedome of expreſſing mens judgements, &amp; if taken in a comprehenſive com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate ſenſe, (King, Lords and Commons) power to repeal old, and Eſtabliſh new Lawes; to which every Subject is bound to yeild obedience: Only thus much let me adde, that no Priviledges of one or both Houſes can Patronize Treaſon, Murder,<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Lex terrae.</hi> J. Jenkens.</note> or breach of the Peace, by their own confeſſion; nor is it indeed conſonant to reaſon; that they, whoſe firſt inſtitution was ordained for preſervation; ſhould themſelves practice or command deſolation; whoſe Conſultations ſhould tend to the prevention of Treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115533:32"/>
and Rebellious excurſions; &amp; their concatenated effects, diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the band of a nationall Peace, effuſion of bloud; by impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (to that purpoſe) penalties &amp; puniſhments upon the offenders; ſhould amidſt ſuch conſultations be practically guilty themſelves of the ſame Crimes; they ſhould be guiltleſs that condemne the guilty.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quae culpare ſoles, ea tu ne feceris ipſe:</l>
               <l>Turpe eſt doctori, cum culpa redarguit ipſum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Preſerve the Liberties of the Kingdomes,</hi> That is, as Kingdomes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving liberties by the Law and Cuſtome thereof diſtinct one from the other;<note place="margin">Covenant.</note> to preſerve each of them, free from any uſurping po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and unlawfull intrenching one upon the Other. And in this reſpect it were to be wiſhed, that our Northern friends had kept cloſe in their practice: and that <hi>England</hi> for the future, would take care to defend its particular Intereſts.</p>
            <p>Liberties of the Kingdomes, not Libertiniſme in a Kingdome. But Liberties, that is, the Liberty of each man therein, which as Natives, or otherwiſe belong unto them according to the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Conſtitution and Law of each reſpective Nation: now this Liberty muſt neceſſarily have a reſpect to all degrees of men therein. Pray then let us not exclude the head of all, the King, as I have touched in my obſervation upon the preamble, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally having ſworn in the next Clauſe to <hi>Preſerve and Defend the Kings Majeſties Perſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That is, Not to hazard His Perſon by oppoſing Armies in the field, where the ignorant Bullet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſtinguiſh perſons; Nor by adminiſtring the leaſt occaſion of heart-grieving &amp; melancholy ſadneſſe; the ſlie, yet certain impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of health, &amp; menacers of the bodies ruine; nor by, and actions or ſpeeches derogatory to the honour of a King, and not becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the duty of a Subject; for you all know what greived <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> moſt; and who it was that ſaid, <hi>At quod tu facis, hoc mihi dolet</hi> — Subjects inſurrections againſt, and inſolent abuſes of their King, (like the apprehenſion of an injury received from an intimate friend) <hi>non tam cito tangit quam penetrat,</hi> like an arrow pierceth the very heart, upon an inſtant, therefore this is not the way to preſerve the Kings perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Covenant. Vide</hi> more to make this good backward.</note>
               <hi>And Authority</hi> — Now, what that is I have already ſhewed, how that to Him belongeth the power of making and repealing Lawes, War or Peace, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115533:32"/>
               <hi>In the preſervation of the true Religion &amp; Liberties of the Kingdom.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This, upon Rationall grounds muſt neceſſarily imply Religion and Liberties, <hi>in eſſe,</hi> not <hi>poſſe</hi> or <hi>velle,</hi> as I have already obſerved; Now both this Religion <hi>in eſſe</hi> by Law eſtabliſhed, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes Liberties: His Majeſty hath preſerved, &amp; ſtil doth, even with the loſſe of his own Defence, the Kingdomes true Liberties. And for His Religion I atteſt His very Enemies confeſſion, to make good His conſtant Perſeverance therein, and preſervation thereof: my ſelf in this particular eſteeming it, <hi>melius ſilere quam pauca dicere,</hi> admiration ſupplying the place of Expreſſion.</p>
            <p>O therefore, that the world may bear witneſſe with your Conſciences of your Loyalty, that is,<note place="margin">Covenant.</note> faithfull obedience to your Soveraigne, (notwithſtanding former aberrations through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) and that you, for your parts had no thoughts or intents to diminiſh that juſt power and greatneſſe which belongeth unto him by the Law: Uſe your beſt endeavours to free Him from this unparallel'd and unjuſt reſtraint, and reſtore Him to His Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall power and poſſeſſion of His Royall prerogative. Thus you will be inſtrumentall reſtorers, of Englands Honour, Peace, and Glory; and doe not content your ſelves, (as too many doe) that you have only ſworn to maintaine the Kings Juſt Rights, when as your actions Endeavour the contrary, or endeavour not at all the maintenance of them, contrary unto this Clauſe of your Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſhall alſo with all faithfullneſſe endeavour the diſcovery of all ſuch as have been, or ſhall be Incendiaries, Malignants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Article. Covenant.</note> 
               <hi>or evill Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by hindring the Reformation of Religion, &amp;c.</hi> Who hindreth Reformation, and a reduction of Religion to the purity of practice, but thoſe who hitherto have countenanced and ſtill connive at a Toleration of all Erroneous practices, Schiſme, &amp;c. contrary to the ſecond Article of this Covenant, hereby making themſelves guilty; for <hi>Qui non vetat peccare cum poteſt, Jubet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dividing the King from His people</hi> — Are not they ſuch divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders who have taken up armes only to deprive His Majeſty of His Regall Power? Declared him not in a condition to governe;<note place="margin">Covenant.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Anſwers to <hi>Scots</hi> Papers, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1647. Dec. Anſwer to <hi>Scots</hi> Papers, 13 <hi>March</hi> 1647.</note> and by impriſonment of Him, diſabled Him from performing His duty as a King, by protecting His Subjects; and by Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons enjoyning their Obedience to the eſtabliſhed Lawes? Who
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115533:33"/>
have divided the Kingdome from the King! but ſuch, as by their actions,<note place="margin">Negat. Oath.</note> Oathes and Declarations have endeavoured to frame <hi>Rem publicam in Regno;</hi> Supreamacy in the people never heard of, nor ever practiſed in this Nation before, in oppoſition to His Majeſties juſtly Supream power; going about to transforme this Kingdome into a body with two heads, which is monſtrous and contrary to nature, and to contrive two ſhining Suns in <hi>Englands</hi> Hemiſphear, which was ever ominous, and Prognoſticatours of Deſtruction.</p>
            <q>O Deus bone, in quae tempora reſervaſti!</q>
            <q>Preſerve us good God from confuſion and ſuddaine ruine.</q>
            <p>Who divide one Kingdom from another, making factions among the people, and cauſing fractions in their duties and affections, but they that invite the aſſiſting invaſion of neighbour Nations, maintaining Armies within its one bowells, to effect an alteration of Government by force? Who divide one Kingdome from another, but they that neglect, nay, deny timely ſupplies, whereby <hi>Ireland</hi> might have been reduced, in Obedience to His Majeſty, and the Law of the Land; the want whereof diſabled the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant party there, and enableth the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts to divide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Crown of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> endangering alſo the ruine of our own Nation; and all theſe contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon rules of Humanity, much more Chriſtianity? and in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition alſo, to the Law of the Land and this League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, thus rightly, Rationally and Religiouſly expounded.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
               <hi>That they,</hi> that is, Incendiaries, Malignants, &amp;c. <hi>may be brought to publick triall, and receive condigne puniſhment as the degree of their Offences ſhall require.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this part of the Article I have nothing to write but this <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Leges fiat Juſtitia,</hi> may Juſtice take place, running down like a ſtream; yet becauſe <hi>non ſanguinis homo; Miſericordia prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valeat opto,</hi> may they all finde pardon for their Treaſon and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt our Soveraign Lord the King, &amp; the Laws in this world, mercy &amp; forgiveneſs for all their ſins againſt the God of Heaven in the world to come. To this purpoſe it were to be wiſhed they would follow the often reiterated advice of Reverend Judge <hi>Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, to reſtore His Majeſty to His Throne, and procure a gracious Pardon from Him, with an all-burying Act of Oblivion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115533:33"/>O that men would in this their day, perceive thoſe wayes wich do lead to Peace and Truth, and walk therein before they be hidden from their eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And whereas the happineſſe of a bleſſed Peace between theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Article Covenant.</note> by the union of the three Kingdomes under One King, profeſſing the truth of Religion, governing by His eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Law; denyed in former times to our Progenitours, is by the providence of God granted unto us, &amp;c. —</p>
            <p>So that, now we are no more Aliens, nay Neighbours, but Brethren; not envying one anothers happineſſe and proſperity, being not infeſted with offenſive or defenſive Acts of hoſtility up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either of our borders, but reciprocally endeavouring one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers peace and welfare, mutually joying in the enjoyment of one anothers happineſſe; Let each of us endeavour that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes may remaine in ſuch a firme peace and union, that is, by our mutuall obedience to our Soveraigne, and the Laws of each reſpective Nation, and in brotherly love one towards another.</p>
            <p>Amen, O heavenly Father. Give us to this end powerfull endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to make good our Covenant accordingly. —</p>
            <p>And may Juſtice be done to the wilfull oppoſers in manner ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the precedent Article.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſhall alſo according to our places in this common cauſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Liberty, and peace of the Kingdomes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Article. Covenant.</note> 
               <hi>aſſiſt and defend by all lawfull meanes all thoſe that enter into this League and Covenant, &amp;c. nor ſhall we make defection to the contrary part, but ſhall oppoſe and hinder</hi> —</p>
            <p>That is, all ſuch who envying our bleſſed union thus religiouſly lawfully cemented, ſhal oppoſe us and it, endeavouring by heretical erroneous divulged poſitions to diſhonour God and robbe him of his glory; by ſeditious doctrines; to infuſe into the people a diſloyal ſpirit of Treaſon and Rebellion againſt the Kings Majeſty His heires and ſucceſſours; of diſobedience to Him and His law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Commands; whereby His honour is deſpiſed, the generall good of the Kingdomes not onely neglected, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut much endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: all which we ſhall do as in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>And becauſe theſe Kingdomes are guilty of many ſins againſt God and his Son Chriſt Jeſus as by our preſent diſtractions &amp; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers too manifeſtly appeareth. Let us all pray that the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth would give us his grace of humiliation for our own
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115533:34"/>
particular, &amp; the general ſins of this Nation, eſpecially that we have not valued the ineſtimable benefit of the Goſpel, nor received Chriſt into our hearts: conforming our lives and actions to his practice and precept; but rather have made uſe of the liberty and freedome which we had by Chriſt from the rigorous exaction and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning power of the Law,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.13.</note> as an occaſion to neglect and altogether to deny our obedience to the Law as the rule of direction. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that thou who art truth it ſelf, haſt told us that the end of thy comming was to fulfill and not to deſtroy the Law;<note place="margin">5 Mat. 17.</note> Nevertheleſſe we deſpiſe it, running madly into ſin as an horſe ruſheth into the battaile. Let us further pray that God would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon us his grace of aſſiſtance, whereby we may be enabled to amend our lives; to performe all holy actions required by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to himſelf, according to his revealed will, all our duties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men according to their ſeverall degrees and places, Honour and obedience to the King as Supreame, to whom they primarily belong; to all ſubordinate Magiſtrates as rivelets ſtreaming from him the Spring; Forgiving all our enemies, perſecutors and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, praying God (who hath the hearts of all men at command, winding them which way he pleaſe as he doth the Rivers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) to pardon their ſins and turne their hearts, and cauſe us to live in love, peace and charity one with another. Thus let us ſhew an example of a reall reformation, that the Lord may turne away his wrath and heavy indignation, and reſtore truth and peace to theſe Churches and Kingdoms, which God out of his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy grant. Amen. Amen.</p>
            <p>To draw to a concluſion, I ſhall (by way of a briefe recollection) propound ſome few queſtions to my poor deceived Country-men which their owne knowledge can anſwer.</p>
            <p>Had the irregular faction of the two Houſes intended as they only pretended a reformation of ſome errours, which perhaps like Cobwebs in an uninhabited houſe, were growne through too much ſecurity a crime incident to an uninterrupted peace in Kingdomes, they might have been ſwep't downe with the milde beeſome of Inſtruction, and care taken to prevent the like for future, and needed not to have pull'd downe the building to take them away.</p>
            <p>Did ever His Majeſty in all His tranſaction by His Meſſages and Declarations ſince theſe unhappy times, propoſe any new thing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115533:34"/>
for the inlargement of His owne Prerogative, or derogatory to the Law of the Land, and more particularly that part thereof which concerneth the Subjects Liberty?</p>
            <p>Did the King Patronize any Inſtruments who ranne former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beyond the juſt bounds of the Law from condigne puniſhment? Did He ever practice Popery truely ſo called, or propoſe any thing that to the moſt jealous and ſuſpicious thoughts might in after-times have occaſioned the introduction thereof?</p>
            <p>Or did he ever adminiſter the leaſt ground to fear his recidiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Proteſtant Religion, but rather hath evidenced the contrary by His Practice, Proclamations, Declarations and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands?</p>
            <p>Did not His Majeſty ever firſt ſend Meſſages of Peace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation;<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>all His Meſſages.</hi> Col. Parl. Ordin.</note> Wooing His Subjects to the enjoyment of their owne Tranquility and happineſſe?</p>
            <p>On the contrary, have not the irregular faction of the two Houſes, notwithſtanding their pretences of Religion and Law; ſubverted the ancient Law and Liberty of our Nation, and defamed the Religion eſtabliſhed abrogating its formes of Worſhip?</p>
            <p>This will appear if you conſider</p>
            <p>That in all their addreſſes though pretending Peace they never endeavoured a reconciliation between His Majeſty and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſuch a manner, whereby a mutuall ſatisfaction and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity might have been given and received as it is requiſite, between two differing parties, but they muſt have all; giving His Majeſty no ſatisction at all?</p>
            <p>Did they ever command the practice of the Religion and formes of worſhip eſtabliſhed (notwithſtanding their pretended maintenance thereof?) or did they ever ſo much as conſult about preſervation thereof, but on the contrary have ſuffered hereſies, Schiſmaticall opinions openly to be Preached and Printed, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the ſame Government?</p>
            <p>Did not His Majeſty yeild to the ſetling of the <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment for three years in a Legall manner, as flowing from the power of the Crowne? But this would not ſatisfie. — They like ſtrange gameſters, fling at all, they muſt have <hi>totaliter totum.</hi> —</p>
            <p>Therefore conſider hereof, you have againe the reſult of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne Epitomized. — <hi>Nolunt hunc regnare.</hi> — Their Writings, Actions, paſt, preſent, (although ſpiced over with never ſo many
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115533:35"/>
plauſible pretences) affirme no leſſe.</p>
            <q>O Angliginae, Angliginae, quae vos dementia cepit?</q>
            <p>O Engliſh-men let me expoſtulate with you; Did all of you, nay did any of you ſix years paſt by your firſt aſſiſtance, intend what you now ſee brought to paſſe? — The frame of your Government altered. — Your King your Soveraigne a Priſoner. I am confident that few or none of you, (you I meane to whom I write, contributers of your aſſiſtance, not knowing wilfull contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers) had then no ſuch intentions; Why then by ſilence will you ſuffer the guilt of theſe bloody deſigners to be originally pinn'd upon your back?</p>
            <p>Take notice that ſin-guilty men are of a nature much like the Plague, they love to have company in infection, avoid the one therefore as you would flie from the other, follow the common Proverbe, Set the ſaddle upon the right horſe.</p>
            <p>Weigh in your thoughts paſt and preſent actions; have they not ſufficiently abuſed you, you deceived, miſlead, <hi>Londoners</hi> I meane?</p>
            <p>Could you ever ſome years paſt, have ſuppoſed that an Army, formerly ſtiling themſelves your protecting friends,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>July</hi> 1647.</note> ſhould by an oppoſing march come againſt you; ſlaying even at your City wals ſome ingaged for your and its defence? that the Cannons mouth ſhould by them be turned againſt your dwellings; that your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive meanes of preſervation within your wals, your Chaines I meane, by the prevalency of that faction, ſhould be knock'd off?</p>
            <p>Could you then expect or fear to be thus domineered over by ſuch bucklers, and the Lording ſwords? I am certaine ſuch thoughts could not then poſſeſſe you. Now, all this being true, why will you by your too too paſſiveneſſe be continuers of your owne Miſeries?</p>
            <p>Conſider further, do you all expect <hi>Clavum regni tenere?</hi> doe you all hope to be Kings? to governe? none obey? you cannot entertaine ſuch vaine conceipts.</p>
            <p>Do you expect that liberty ſhould be granted in Civill affaires? <hi>Vitam ſine lege vivere</hi> to live without a Law. — No no: deceive not your ſelves — your cunning Maſters that have hitherto blindfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you and led you by the noſe; will, when they have gained the full command of the reines, make you paſſive in any thing that their ambition, malice, and covetouſneſſe ſhall (though falſely)
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115533:35"/>
ſuggeſt as neceſſary and convenient. — Therefore be perſwaded to a deſertion of them and their deſignes. What though you have got a ſcratch or two in your reputation, by your former er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous actions; would you rather have it feſter through neglect, and ſo indanger the loſſe of a member, then apply this ſalve of a penitentiall returne, which will heale you in a moment? <hi>Non eſt pernicioſum in praelio vulnerari, ſed poſt vulnus acceptum vulneri medicamentum non applicare;</hi> It is more madneſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe a cure, then diſhonour to receive a wound.</p>
            <p>Is it not a far better, happier Government, and freer from oppreſſion to live under our Soveraigne Lord the King, Ruling His Subjects by a written Law, and reſigning the Miniſters of that Law (if they neglect executing Juſtice and Judgement according to the direction thereof) to the ſtrictly ſearching examination of a Parliament, (one of their proper workes) and according to their merit by them to receive Puniſhment, then under a company of Tyrannicall perſons <hi>(quibus voluntates ſolummodo leges)</hi> gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning according to their owne wils, and from whom there is no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale?</p>
            <p>Once more therefore, let me earneſtly deſire all my abuſed and deceived Country-men, to returne to the God of heaven by a true and unfeigned repentance to their Soveraigne in Loyall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and obedienciall actions, to their Country in a true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fidelity.</p>
            <p>And here although I have not the leaſt cauſe (knowing the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion on which they ſtand, to doubt their contrary practice) yet for the further advancement of His Majeſties Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, their owne reputations as <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants, Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kings ſo juſt a Cauſe, and ſtopping the mouthes of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious men, who watch for reviling opportunities, let me adde this requeſt, to all thoſe who by the aſſiſting and directing power of the Almighty God have ever ſince theſe diſmall dayes of bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diſloyalty, been kept in the ſtraight path of obedience to His Majeſty, That they would invite all former wanderers out of that way, unto a returne, by perſwaſive arguments of reaſon, ſound principles of Religion, alluring expreſſions of affection, laying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all bitterneſſe of ſpirit, revenge and hatred, the bane of Peace and reconciliation, forgetting all former deviations; putting a difference between the efficient and inſtrumentall cauſe, I meane
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115533:36"/>
the contrivers of this Rooting deſigne and the Inſtruments, who were abuſed into unlawfull actions by ſpecious pretences, and know not the end to which theſe beginnings did tend; conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that though Nature hath equally beſtowed eyes upon all birds, yet ſhe hath not given to all, eyes alike qualified with the Eagles; therefore let us all rather endeavour to cleare their ſight, then muffle them with the vailes of ſcornefull and reproachfull words; Nay let us even to the moſt wilfull perſiſters and invenomed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits imitate the example of bleſſed S. <hi>Steven,</hi> whoſe heart, hands, eyes, and tongue then begg'd mercy and forgiveneſſe of the God of heaven, for his hard hearted adverſaries, when they were knocking him downe to the earth with ſtones. And when in after times the wheel ſhall turne, placing their expectations in the chaire of power with a <hi>nunc fruimur votis,</hi> forget not to uſe the reines of command with Moderation; ſtill remembring that the irregular deeds of State affaires, and Princes imployed inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, reflect alwayes upon their Royall Maſter; the Kings ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour being then wounded when they do but ſlip into the practice of unwarrantable, unjuſt oppreſſing actions, remembring alſo that many thouſands in <hi>England</hi> have almoſt for ſeaven years time, been bred up like wilde Colts, by their Riders, unto ſtubborneſſe and diſobedience, and therefore in probability, may ſooner be ſtroked then whipp'd into a condeſcending compliance; for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes we know, that the ſence of an immoderately beating hand, forceth a penitentiall, (though formerly prodigall child) to a backſliding, and re-excurſions, unto more deſperate underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings.</p>
            <p>Although <hi>England</hi> hath been long troubled almoſt with a general phrenzie, yet the Iron rod, Bread and Water are not properly to be given them as food, whom Time the mother of Truth, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction the Judgements Informer, hath like Phyſick recovered from that diſtemper.</p>
            <p>Remember that <hi>England</hi> hath been long ſick of a Conſumption, even to a fear'd diſſolution of the whole body, like a Patient (by the loſſe of much blood) brought into an extreame weakeneſſe; and all know, that knowing Phyſitians (although probably there may ſtill remaine ſome bad humour) adminiſter not ſtrong Purges, but comforting Cordials then, when there is as it were an <hi>interreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num inter mortem vitam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi> not knowing which will be the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115533:36"/>
life or death; ſtill having in your thoughts that it is the onely glorious property of mercy, for a man then to pardon and forgive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries when it is in his power to be revenged. Thus let us win all unto us, and being won, lock their affections and judgements by ſuch Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian-like examples, and like true followers of Chriſt pray for all men, firſt for our Soveraigne Lord King <hi>Charls</hi> to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>O Thou Lord of Hoſts, pitch thou thy tent hourely round about Him; be a ſhield to defend Him from all violent attempts againſt His Royall Perſon, from cunning inſinuations againſt His Honour, Crowne and Dignity, be thou good God His comforter in this His day of Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; permit not the waters of affliction to overwhelme His ſoul with ſadneſſe, but continually ſupply Him with patience proportionable to His ſufferings: haſten, haſten good Father His deliverance. Reſtore Him unto His Regall Power and juſt Rights, ſettle Him, ſettle Him faſt in His Throne; place the Crown upon His head, and ſuffer it not by the hands of Treaſon or Rebellion to be ſhaked, or removed from Him, or any of His Royall off-ſpring untill <hi>Shiloh</hi> come; Bleſſe His Majeſties Royall Conſort, our moſt gracious Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> cauſe Her with <hi>Mary</hi> in the Goſpel to chooſe that better part which never can be taken from Her. Bleſſe, protect and defend our Noble Prince <hi>Charls,</hi> with the reſt of His Majeſties Princely Progeny: Bleſſe theſe Kingdomes of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all degrees of men therein, from the higheſt to the loweſt: Forgive the iniquity of the people, turne us O Lord, from our ſins, and we ſhall be turned, take away the heavy judgement of the ſword from us, Reſtore our Peace, renew and continue our Plenty, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us according to the dayes wherein thou haſt afflicted us, according to the years that we have ſeen evil;</hi> Take away all bitterneſſe of ſpirit, revenge, hatred, and give us unity, brotherly love, and concord.</p>
            <p>Bleſſe the famuos City of <hi>London;</hi> grant the Inhabitants a ſerious conſideration of their former wayes, repentance and pardon for all their offences; turne them, turne them O Lord into thy paths, <hi>Let thy word be a Light unto their feet, and thy teſtimonies a guide unto their ſtep.</hi> Reſtore unto them their ancient Government, and to that end give them Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, Magiſtrates, and all other Officers according to thy own will; Religious, not Rebellious, faithfull, not factious, carefull to diſcharge that truſt which God and His Scared Majeſty ſhal intruſt them with, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding thy Law for their imitation; the knowne Laws of the Land for their direction, ſtudying onely the glory of thee our God, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Royall Soveraigne and His Poſterity, The peace and plenty,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115533:37"/>
wealth and weale, proſperity and happineſſe of all their fellow Citizens, from the greateſt to the leaſt and meaneſt. Preſerve them and the whole City from the boundleſſe rage of devouring fire, from Plague, peſtilenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all diſeaſes &amp; famine, defend it from the ravenous violence of maliciouſly ambitious men, from being tyrannized over &amp; oppreſſed by the inſulting ſword: let not, O let not the wealth and glory thereof, nor any of the Inhabitants be expoſed a prey to the unſatiable fury of avaricious, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengefull, blood-thirſty men: purge it from all hereſie, ſchiſme, profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and whatſoever is contrary to thy word and Commandments; and to this purpoſe beſtow upon them faithful diſpenſers of thy Word, feeing their flocks with wholſome food; not leading them unto Rockie Mountaines to famiſh, nor leaving them amongſt Wolves, killing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, to be deſtroyed, not giving the children of thy family either for fear or hope, <hi>ſtones inſtead of bread, Serpents in place of Fiſhes;</hi> not Preaching themſelves but the Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, in truth and ſincerity. <hi>O Let not my Lord be angry and I will ſpeak but this once;</hi> Be thou, (O Almighty, Omnipotent God) a ſtrong tower of defence to all the particular Citizens, Members of that Honourable Corporation, with all the reſt of the people within His Majeſties Realms and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, high and low, rich and poor, young and old, even from our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Lord the King, to the tender infant newly ſtept into the world out of the darke priſon of the wombe, and together with them all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers belonging to His Royall<note n="*" place="margin">Eng. Scot. Irel.</note> Family and houſehold whereſoever di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed; Take thou every one of them into thy all-ſecuring protection, give them bleſſings proportionable to their ſeverall degrees, conditions and neceſſities, ſhowre downe thy bleſſings upon all men from one end of the earth to the other; Let the ſun-ſhine of thy Goſpel breake forth in all dark corners of the world, diſpelling the black clouds of Judaiſme, Turciſme, Paganiſme, and all other Errours whatſoever: Accompliſh the number of thy Elect, and then come Lord Jeſus, come quickly. Grant theſe Petitions O thou Father of all mercies and God of all conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for the ſake of thy Son our Saviour, to whom with thee and thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, be aſcribed all Honour and Glory, now and for evermore. <hi>Amen. Amen. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Soli Deo gloria.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Si quid novisti rectius iſtis</l>
                  <l>Imperti, ſi non, his utere mercum.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
